welcome to the JANUARY meeting
of san fan board of supervisors.
Will you call the roll?
>> thank you.
MR. PRESIDENT.
Supervisor chan.
>> present
>> supervisor chen.
>> present.
>> supervisor dorsey.
>> supervisor engardio.
>> present.
>> supervisor fielder.
>> supervisor mahmood.
>> present
>> supervisor mandelman.
>> present.
>> supervisor melgar.
>> supervisor sauter.
>> present.
>> supervisor sherrill.
>> and supervisor walton.
>> present
>> MR. PRESIDENT all members are
present.
>> thank you, it has been
pointed out itted g afternoon.
Everyone.
>> the san francisco board of
supervisors acknowledges we are
on the home lanltdz of the
ramaytush ohlone who are the
original inhab tanlts of the san
francisco peninsula as stewards
of the land they have never cd
lost or forgotten their
responsibilities as care takeers
of the place and all people in
their traditional territories.
We recognize we benefit from
living and working on their home
land we acknowledge the
ancestors and elders of the
ramaytush ohlone community and
aif he wering their rights as
first people.
Colleagues, will you join me in
the pledge?
[Pledge of allegiance] On
behalf of our board I
acknowledge the staff at sfgovtv
colleena mendoza who records and
makes tripses available online.
Are there communication.
>> I have none.
>> go to the approval of
meeting minutes.
>> colleagues we're approving
minute for DECEMBER 17, 2024
regular board meeting are there
changes to the minutes?
Can I have a motion to approve
the minutes as presented.
Moved by walten seconded by
chen.
Will you call the roll.
>> on the minutes as presented
supervisor dorsey.
>> aye.
>> supervisor engardio.
>> supervisor fielder.
>> aye.
>> supervisor mahmood.
>> supervisor mandelman.
>> aye.
>> supervisor melgar.
>> supervisor sauter.
>> aye.
>> supervisor sherrill.
>> supervisor walton.
>> aye.
>> supervisor chan.
>> supervisor chen.
>> ayech
>> there are 11 aye's.
Wroo all right.
Without objection the minutes
will be approved after public
comment as presented.
>> mad dam clerk our 2 P.M.
Special order.
>> 2 P.M. Order the apparentlies
of today's meeting by the
honorable mayor daniel lurie to
engage in a policy discussion
with board members.
The discussion the mayor MAY
address the board for up to 5
minutes.
>> welcome, MR. Mayor.
Mayor lurie do you have opening
remarks.
>> good afternoon PRESIDENT
Mandelman and board colleagues.
Two weeks ago I introduced my
legislative proposal.
The upon fentanyl state
emergency.
Since is visited sixth street 8
or 9 times and last week I
walked throughout tenderloin
with supervisor mahmood.
Where we encountered a woman
that I met many times during my
visits walk nothing soma and the
tenderloin.
She was on the street struggling
with addiction with no clear
plan to enter in treatment.
Her store seunfortunately far
too common and urgent and
sobering reminder of the
challenges we must address.
People in our city need our help
now.
What we have been doing is not
working.
Our city needs to move with the
urgency this crisis demands.
It is my hope that through our
legislation we will be able to
quickly expand treatment and
shelter capacity.
Implement behavioral and mental
health initiatives and hiring of
key public safer and behavioral
health staff we are engaging
with everyone of your offices
and hope we can show san
francisco a united front on this
piece of legislation.
We might not always agree on
every issue.
You have my commitment this
we'll engage in the spirit of
collaboration.
That that we will work to find
common ground.
And go through amendments line
by line.
I want to thank my cosponsors
supervisors dorsey, engardio u
sherrill, mahmood and sauter.
I want to thank PRESIDENT
Mandelman for granting this
legislation a 30-day waiver ato
move quickly through the
legislative process.
I want to thank supervisor chan
for scheduling this item at
tomorrow's budget and finance
and for engaging my office on
the amendments.
With that, I yield my time and
say, thanks.
>> thank you, mayor lurie.
Call the topic.
>> yes, skilled nursing.
Home needs and senior services
in the richmond submitted by
supervisor connie chan.
>> supervisor chan.
Thank you, welcome MR. Mayor,
good to see you.
As we than long standing skilled
insing facility in the richmond
will close in APRIL.
Many reached out wanting to know
the future of the site and
ensuring that seniors are taken
care of.
We know that d1 and san
francisco are at the deficit for
the types of facilities and
service.
We cannot afford to lose another
facility.
our vision is for the city to
identify partners that can help
us in home as a resource for our
community and develop the site
for other critical resource for
ascertains and many in the
richmond and throughout san
francisco what is your mission
for the site. And how can we
partner together on delivering a
joint vision to supporting our
seniors in the rich manned and
beyond.
Thank you.
>> thank you for your question.
Supervisor chan.
First I want to share my
sympathy with the residents for
the closure of st.S anns.
This is I challenging time and
you have my commitment the city
will support you through this
transiing.
Laguna honda stepped up to
support st. Ann's families
through this.
I'm pleased share all who meet
admissions criteria at laguna
honda have space available to
them ensuring they can continue
care.
We must a broader strategy for
supporting seniors to live and
engaged in their communities.
As a city, san francisco
repeated 3 shown strong
commitment to our seniors and
that will continue as long as
I'm mayor.
The department of disability and
aging services plays a vital
role in this effort.
Providing resources over 70,000
older and disabled adultsanualy.
Include siteds base and home
based services taylored meet
needs.
And d1, 1 in 4 seniors accesses
gas services a program is in
home support services you know
well, supervisor, helps 1500
senior in d within remain in
homes.
By assisting them with daily
activities like dressing and
meal preparation.
Regarding the future we will
look forward to conversations
with the little sisters about
the site's potential, it is
early to know the future of the
site we are committed to working
for all possibilityings.
You have my assurance we will
engage with the department of
public health, das, mohcd and
your office to ensure all
options for the site are
carefully vetd and considered.
Together we will work toward
common solutions.
If I MAY, I want to add
something separate.
Thank you for inviting mow for
lunch today.
>> [Laughter].
I will come to your side of the
house often.
>> we have noticed that.
Glad you could drop by.
Thank you.
Supervisor chan you MAY ask a
follow up question related to
the opening question.
It looks like supervisor chan is
going to pass on this.
And -- mayor lurie you MAY ask a
question to supervisor chan or
other supervisor in attendance
pertaining to the same topic but
in the related to the previous
question if you so desire.
I wanted to know when I'm
invited back for lunch.
>> wow.
>> [Laughter].
Thank you all for having me.
Thank you, PRESIDENT.
>> thank you, MR. Mayor.
all right.
This -- let's see.
This concludes the d1 topic
discussion.
And -- concludes our mayor
And the matter has been discussd
and now filed.
>> all right.
MADAM Clerk.
Could you talk us to consent
2-4?
>> yes.
2-4 are on consent.
These items are considered to be
routine if a member objects an
item MAY be removed and
considered separate low
>> colleagues, does anyone wish
to sever an item from consent?
I don't see anyone.
MADAM Clerk.
Call the role
>> on 2-4 supervisor dorsey.
>> aye.
>> supervisor engardio.
>> supervisor fielder.
>> aye.
>> supervisor mahmood.
>> aye
>> supervisor mandelman.
>> aye.
>> supervisor melgar.
>> supervisor sauter.
>> aye
>> supervisor sherrill.
>> aye.
>> supervisor walton.
>> supervisor chan.
>> aye.
>> and supervisor chen.
>> there are 11 aye's.
>> without objection they are
passod first reading the
resolution is adopted.
MADAM Clerk the regular agenda
unfinished business item 5
>> item 5 an ordinance to amend
planning code and zoning map to
create the 30 van ness special
use district in the area bounds
by feld to the north.
Market street and van ness to
modify the special restrictions
relateded to inclusionary
housing obligations.
And to affirm the ceqa and make
the appropriate findings.
Colleagues, MADAM Clerk that I
can this same house same call.
Wowed objection this is finally
passed.
>> can you call next 6 and 7
together.
Why 6 and 7 are an ordinance and
resolution the resolution
authorizes the issuance and sale
of 40 million in aggregate
amount of -- taxable general
obligation bonds for affordable
housing 2016 preservation and
seismic safety.
Series 25e and a authorizes the
form and terms of said bonds.
Appointment of other agents the
establishment of accounts
related to bonds authorize the
notice of sale and the notice of
intention to sale bonds by
competitive or negotiated sale
and approve the forms
publication and the form of the
bond purchase contract and the
ordinance item 6, appropriates
40 million of general bond
proceeds to the mayor's office
of how doing and community
development to acquire, improve
and rehab and convert at risk
multiunit residential buildings
to permanent affordable house
and on controller reserve
pending the sales of the bonds
from 2-25.
>> take these items same house
same call.
without objection.
The ordinance is passed.
The resolution is adopted.
Can you call item 8.
>> item 8 resolution to approve
and authorize the general
manager of the puc to execute
the third amendment to
professional services agreement.
For mountain tunnel improvement
conduction services with
technical services inc. To
increase the conticket by 9.5
million a new contract of 34
million and 5 month contract
extension for a contract term
JULY 31, 2019 through DECEMBER
30 of 27 to provide specialized,
construction management service
for the mountain tunnel improve
am project pursuant to charter
9.118.
>> we can take this same house
same call without objection.
Can you call item 9.
A resolution to authorize the
police department to accept and
extend a 23 thousand dollars
donation pursuant to the order
of revised distribution of the
margaret extension living trust
to the prepare mounted unit.
>> and MADAM Clerk, same house
same call.
Without objection the resolution
is adopted.
Can you call item 10.
>> item 10 a resolution to
retroauthorize the office of
economic and w force development
to accept and extend an
approximately 497 thousand
dollars grant from the james
irvine foundation for public
workforce capacity funds during
the period of NOVEMBER of 24
through NOVEMBER of 26.
>> and we can take this same
house same call without
objection it is adopted.
madam clerk.
Call item 11.
>> item upon 11 resolution to
retroauthorize the office of the
the city attorney to accept and
extend a 410 thousand dollars
guarantee from the california
department of industrial
relations labor commissioners
office.
To funds the enforcement of
labor laws AUGUST 24 through
JULY of 25.
>> take this item same house
same call.
Without objection it is adopted.
Can you call items 12 and 13
together.
>> items 12 and then are two
resolutions pertain to
agreements between the office of
contract administration, and the
following companies for item 12
this is withful corporation dbi
pesteck for pest management
services for 5 year term through
FEBRUARY 14 of 2030 for 15.5
million.
And item 13 for mail room
equipment and postage and term
of throw years through JANUARY
31 of 28.
With an additional 2 year option
for 23. 5 million.
>> we can take these same
house same call without
objection they are adopted.
Can you call item 14.
>> item 14 a resolution it
approve and authorize the mayor
and the director of the mayor's
office of housing and community
development to execute a first
amendment to the loan agreement
relate to an upon loan to
acquire the report at 2530, 18th
intended for development of 100%
affordable multifamily rental
families for a new loern amount
6.9 million and aggregate
funding amount of 11. 8 million.
>> we can take this same house
same call without objection.
MADAM Clerk.
Item 15
>> item 15 a resolution to
authorize the mayor's office of
housing and communities
development to execute and
submit an application for
guarantee under the prosecute
housing incentive program
administered by california
department of housing and
community development 1. 5
million in program funding
through JANUARY first, 2028.
>> and we can take this item
same house same call without
objection, adopted.
Can you please call item 16
>> item 16.
Resolution to retroauthorize the
department of public health to
accept and extend a 750 thousand
dollars grant from the
california department of health
care service through fapgz and
program san francisco department
of public health behavioral
health service children, youth
and families modular approach to
therapy for children with
anxiety, depression, trauma or
conduct problems.
OCTOBER 4, 2024 through JUNE 30
of 25.
>> we can take this item same
house same call it is adopted.
MADAM Clerk item 17.
>> item 17, a resolution to
authorize the rpd to accept and
extend 750 thousand in grant
funds from the metro
transportation commission for
the visitation of a new bicycle
and pedestrian safety
improvement project grant
performance expect exclude
contract execution through
august 30, 2029.
To approve the grant contract
this requires rpd to operate and
maintain it 420 years commencing
preponder project completion
pursuant to 9.118
>> chair chan.
>> thank you, PRESIDENT
Mandelman my apologies, we
should have taken care of this
during the budget committee.
I neglected strike 2 clauses
that you sought amendmentos page
3 line through 7.
And it is irrelevant allowing
the now the item has been heard
at budget and finance committee
they should go ahead and accept
and extend the grant.
So I would like to make the
motion to shut the two clauses
amending legislation and that
urge to you support the
legislation.
>> unanimously.
I hope.
>> thank you for that motion.
Supervisor chan.
Is there a second?
>> seconded by supervisor
dorsey.
Colleagues, can we take these
ma'ams without objection?
I think we can.
These are approved.
MADAM Clerk take this item as
amended same house same call.
Without objection it is adopted
as amended.
>> can you call item 18.
>> item 18 a resolution to
approve the settle am of the
unlitigated claims by stripe
inc. Against the city for 49
million.
The claims involve payroll
extendful homelessness gross
receipts over paid gross
receipts and commercial rent
taxes.
and business registration fees.
Other terms of the settlement
relate to stripes filing
position with respect to city
taxes.
>> and I think we can take this
same house same call without
objection it is adopted.
Can you call item 19
>> ordinance to amend the
planning code to permit certain
health service use up to 5,000
with a cu in the westportal
commercial district and
aanywhere the ceqa and make
promote findings.
>> and I think we can take this
same house same call without
objection passed on first
reading.
Call item 20.
>> item 20 an ordinance to
accept irrevokable offers of
public infrastructure with the
sunnydale hope sf project fizz 2
to include offer of improvements
for infrastructure and
dedication for real property
under lying a portion of
sunnydale avenue to dedicate the
public improve ams for use and
public street and purposes and
sept public infrastructure for
city maintenance and liability
purposes.
Subject to limitedations and
additional low to establish the
official street grade to amend
ordinance number 1061 entitled
relating the width of sidewalk
tos establish it on sunnydale
and accept the public works
order recommending various
actions in regard to the public
infrastructure improvements and
adopt the appropriate findings.
>> without objection.
Colleagues I think we can take
this samous same call the
ordinance is passed on first
read.
Call item 21
>> item 21 resolution to
authorize and accept and record
132 easements from various
property owner in san mateo
required for the airport's noise
installation program the ceqa
and mech the appropriate
findings.
>> and again we can take this
same house and call without
objection it is adopted.
Call item 22.
>> this is an ordinance to amend
the code to reestablish the
african-american arts and
cultural advisory commitment
from city departments describing
the cultural @bye-byes of the
arty district and acknowledge
and preserve the cultural legacy
of the district.
Sfm we can take this same house,
same call without objection it
is passed on first read.
Can you call item 23?
>>.
23 this is an ordinance to amend
the administrative code to
extend the sunset date for the
cannabis oversight committee
from JANUARY of 25 to JANUARY of
27 and to provide that the
ordinance shall be retroto yell
of 25.
>> okay.
I think we can take this same
house and call it is passed on
first reading.
And we have 4 minutes before
roll call, I think.
>> reports.
>> no committee reports
>> committee reports 29 thereof
32 considered by rules on monday
JANUARY 27, 25.
And were forwarded as committee
reports.
Item 29.
recommend as amended bearing the
same title.
An ordinance to amend the code
to create the cole valley
entertainment zone between
frederick and per nanceis and
carl street to delete the
requirements as an entertainment
zone event the special events
permitted or licensed by
alcoholic beverage control and
affirm ceqa determination.
>> and I think we can take this
same house same call.
Ordinance is passed on first
reading.
>> can you call item 30?
>> this is an ordinance to
amend the code to add the bay
area law enforcement assistance
funds city officers and
employees MAY make donations by
payroll deduction.
>> same house same call without
objection the ordinance is
passed on first reading.
In dam clerk, please call item
>> item 31 a motion to reappoint
supervisor engardio to the
golden gate bridge highway and
transportation district board of
directors term ending JANUARY
31, 27 or conconclusion of his
term as member of the board of
supervisors.
>> colleagues can a have a
motion to excuse supervisor
engardio.
>> moved, is there a second.
By walton.
MADAM Clerk call the role
>> on the motion to excuse
supervisor engardio.
Sprierdz dorsey
>> aye
>> supervisor engardio will be
excused
>> supervisor fielder
>> aye
>> supervisor mahmood.
>> supervisor mandelman.
>> aye.
>> supervisor melgar.
>> aye joovm supervisor sauter.
>> aye.
>> supervisor sherrill.
>> aye
>> supervisor walton.
>> aye.
>> supervisor chan.
>> aye joovm supervisor chen.
>> aye.
>> there are 10 aye's.
>> without objection.
We excused supervisor engardio.
On the motion MADAM Clerk call
the roll
>> supervisor dorsey.
>> aye.
>> supervisor fielder.
>> supervisor mahmood.
>> aye.
>> supervisor mandelman.
>> aye
>> supervisor melgar.
>> aye.
>> supervisor sauter.
>> supervisor sherrill.
>> aye.
>> supervisor walton.
>> supervisor chan.
>> aye.
>> supervisor chen.
>> aye
>> there are 10 aye's
>> without objection it is
approved and supervisor engardio
is going back on to the golden
gate bridge board.
Congratulations, entires, thank
you for your service.
MADAM Clerk item 32.
>> item 32 a motion to
reappoint supervisor walton not
bay area air quality manage the
board of directors ending
FEBRUARY first of 29 or the
conclusion of term as member of
the board of supervisors.
>> colleagues can I have a
motion to intruz supervisor
walton.
Moved and seconded by chen.
Can you call the roll.
>> on the motion to excuse
supervisor walton from item 32
>> dorsey
>> aye
>> engardio.
>> supervisor fielder.
>> aye
>> supervisor mahmood.
>> aye.
>> supervisor mandelman.
>> supervisor melgar.
>> aye.
>> supervisor sauter.
>> supervisor sherrill.
>> aye.
>> supervisor chan.
>> aye
>> supervisor chen.
>> aye.
There are 10 aye's.
>> thank you, without objection
supervisor walton is excused on
the motion will you call the
roll
>> supervisor dorsey.
>> ayech
>> supervisor engardio.
>> aye.
>> supervisor fielder.
>> supervisor mahmood.
>> aye.
>> supervisor mandelman.
>> ayech
>> supervisor melgar.
>> supervisor sauter.
>> aye
>> supervisor sherrill.
>> aye.
>> supervisor chan.
>> supervisor chen.
>> aye.
There are 10 aye's
>> all right without objection
it is approved.
And supervisor walton is going
back and thank you for your
service on that body.
>> let's go to our 2:30 special
order.
Recognition of commendations
from service to the city and
county of san francisco.
>> we got 2 commendations
today.
Let's start with supervisor
melgar.
>> thank you so much.
PRESIDENT Mandelman.
Colleagues, today I have the
honor of recognizing the
distinguished career of monica
walters.
A dedicated advocate.
[Applause] For san francisco
children and families.
Monica arrived in san francisco
in 2009 after a long career
working for nonprofit in
washington state.
Upon arrival she got to work
helping our most under served
children and families.
In our city especially members
of the a ap I community.
Monica served on the steering
committee of the ap I council.
The board of chinese health
coalition and domestic violence
consortium.
In 2012.
She took a new position as ceo
of wuyee children service taking
overnight role that my former
colleague our former pedestrian
board yee had before he was
elected.
She fulfilled the promise of
shifth to a multilingual and
racial service bottle expanding
services in the san francisco
block next and islander
community.
She lead the charge to expand
the early learning centers from
6-12.
Becoming the largest head start
program.
In 2018 she took a role in the
community effort to pass the
baby prop c.
And later served the every
childhood community advisory
committee.
Helping ensure that funding was
directed to san francisco early
childhood education system as
voters intended.
She consistently demonstrated
dedication to providing san
francisco's most vulnerable
children and families with the
childcare and early education
services this they deserve.
She has never been afraid to
speak truth to power and to
fight for and passionate low for
our babies and children in
families in san francisco.
With your help we'll continue to
push for a universal early care
and education system.
I would like to thank her for
her many years serving the city
and the people of san francisco.
I wish her the very best.
As she entered retirement.
I know she will be bodies.
We have a resolution later on
the agenda, colleagues and that
will recognize her for all her
work.
For the years.
With that, MR. PRESIDENT.
I would like to ask monica to
come up and share a few words.
[Applause] Got my precious
granddaughter with me today to
celebrate this honor.
PRESIDENT Mandelman, and members
of the board of supervisors, my
deepest thanks.
For this special recognition
today.
As supervisor melgar said I come
before this body to request your
support for the early childcare
service to the health and
success of children and families
in the city.
Ceo chair feedback and member of
the council and in partnership
with other great service
agencies.
Supervisor melgar you have been
a leader following the foot
steps of supervisor yee and all
my greatest appreciation and
gratitude to you and your staff
who have really helped protect
this such an important part of
the values of san francisco.
A true statement to our values
as a great city in the
commitment to our kids.
Working there has been the
greatest joy and highlight of my
career in the nonprofit field
this amazing agency accomplishes
so much do to the dedication and
skill of the wonderful staff.
Some of whom are here today.
Together we have weathered the
pandemic accident built new
centers, launched new programs
like our new workforce path
way's program and subsidies for
family in san francisco.
I would not stand here were not
for them caring daily to make
sure our babies are safe and
learning more each day and
keeping our financials and
contracts in order, too.
>> my thanks to mark or cfo.
sheryl director of early
learning.
And my most faithful and
wonderful executive assist
knowant kimmoson.
I topped extend graft tu to
partner agencies that also stood
with me throughout the years.
Mission naushd centerses the frc
alliance and ap I council to
name a few and of course my
mentor and friends former
PRESIDENT And ed norman yee.
I want to thifrng my family.
They have been my biggest source
of love and support and another
reason I chose this path for my
life's work.
Brightest life in my world and I
can't wit to spend more time
with them.
I expect to enjoy my retirement
not to stop and advocacy and
commitment to contribute what I
can to bring true equity in the
lives of all of our children in
san francisco.
Thank you again this has been a
tremendous honor for me.
[Applause]
>> all right.
That brings you to d8.
Tony.
Come on up.
[Applause].
And bring anyone you want to
bring with you.
Colleagues -- today I'm offering
a special commendation to
teamster local 6 sick 5.
1 huh human scombroers a day
going in 19 twist broorth hood
granted a charter to team sters
and helpers union local 665.
Prior to that time, throughout
1906 quake, flew of 1918 the san
francisco stable man's union,
had organized and represented
first the stable men who
maintained horse carriages and
workers in the autoindustry.
Born in the 20's local 665 rose
to meet challenges of a new day
the boomingly economy and
expansion of the commercial
sector required autoand parking
services and members were there
to meet the needs.
Team sters members worked on
again/off again street park,
rental cars and grow dealerships
the membership was awarded with
wages, benefit and working
conscience the envy of other
regions in the us.
Overnight challenge they xnldzed
geography, jurisdiction and
credits arrangemented.
Today they represent workers in
parcel delivery, construction,
food processing bus
transportation.
Weight and recycling airport
services and the core autopark
and industry trades throughout
northern california.
A century after founding we
celebrate the contributions of
team steer 6 sick 5 member who
is moved the economy of the bay
area. And local 665 at the
forefront to ensure that amid
the innovations and dislocations
of our economic moment, as we
seen concentration of economic
and political power and few are
hands that workers and families
not left behind.
I know I can speak for my
colleague when is I say it has
been our honor to be part of
some efforts I suspect that at
least a few MAY want to speak
for themselves.
Yesterday I number of us went to
the [Inaudible] The mayor and
bay area and california in
celebrating the anniversary.
And I will note that tony was
wearing a tie yesterday.
[Laughter].
I knew I would be remiss in
duties at pedestrian this body
if I did not request and insist
this teamster local 6 sick 5
come back for this board
commends anticipation.
Accepting it we have tony the
principal officer of local 665
northern california the central
valley and northern nevada you
are ready to speak I knew it my
colleaguement to talk.
Supervisor walton.
Thank you.
I will be brooefr I want to say
to tony to joe and the entire
local 665 team sters we
appreciate all the work that you
do for workers and for
community.
You worked through the pandemic.
You continue to support folks
who need you the most and I want
to thank you for all the work I
want to say happy 1 huh human
year anniversary and you could
not ask for bert than you get
from tony.
Thank you for the work you do
with the commune as well.
Thank you.
Thank you we cannot let tony do
all the talks.
I get on have a word today to
thank you for the leadership.
Thank you for representing the
working people that need your
representation in types like
this.
It was moving yesterday.
To hear the history that tony
laid out for us to hear all the
counterparts and hear remarks
about really fighting for the
people.
And I truly that and honored to
be here congratulating you and
celebrating you.
You are for the people and that
i'm grateful for your
partnership for the legislations
we wod together.
And I know this there is a tough
fight ahead of us.
There are many challenges but
having leadership like you all
you here I think this is the
works people in san francisco
and the bay area can be comfortd
and to know that we have a
better future ahead of us.
Thank you.
>> thank you, supervisor
fielder?
>> hello tony, and all of the
officers here today.
Thank you for inviting me
yesterday to your celebration.
Congratulations.
I know we have not gotten too
much [Inaudible] From what the
little I had to get to know you.
I know tell be a fun 4 years but
and all honesty, my office is
always open.
You other backbone of san
francisco and bright are future
for all families.
Thank you all.
Supervisor guard gar.
You are a great student of
history.
I do a popular politics
presentation I need to add and
include a lot of what you talked
about yesterday.
I think it is it does not matter
if you are a teamster it is
important to adopt and
innovative and creative and
under lying all that with a
mission to help work and people
the teamsters have done that
starting 25 years before you
were chartered.
As new technologies came you
were able to lead the way I'm
can you feeled lead the way in
the next handled years.
thank you for your service.
>> supervisor chen.
>> hi, tony.
Thank you for inviting me to
your celebration to
congratulations and I want to
express my heart felt thank you
and appreciation to the work you
are doing and leading the
organization and fighting for
workers in the city and keeping
families in the city.
And thank you so much and I wish
you another hundred years of
success.
>> thank you.
>> thank you, supervisor.
>> tony thank you for coming
become for a second day of being
honored. Floor is yours.
>> before I start I see two
minutes I was promised 5.
You got 5.
PRESIDENT Mandelman and the
board, thank you for honoring us
again.
I will keep it brief 9 or 10 of
you were here yesterday I don't
want to repeat myself plus the
PRESIDENT Took away half of my
speech I gotta ad-lib.
Joking.
Aloft work with you know 6 of
you.
I want to welcome the 5
supervisors this is the first
time I'm seeing you in your
seats mahmood, field and chan
chen and sought are look forward
to working with you.
I talked to since have been
elected you will be on board
with the same ideas we have.
Men and women.
So, really quickil do it quick.
It is important I will touch
brief on what I said it is a bit
of a repeat.
The union was put together in
1900 by 200 workers seeking to
advance to help them and
families grooming horses, and
chores for pen essay day stable
men 'union they gave them gains
but problems.
The earthquake.
Pandemic and we had a world war.
So, powerful people and
employers in the city were
trying to get rid of the union
then.
They were trying to test the
strength.
And so a few years later.
The international broth of team
sters came in 1925 on JANUARY
27.
Exactly a handled years and a
day ago.
There were a well established
youn that had thousands coast to
coast.
And times were changing in the
industrial age.
Horses would turn to
automobiles.
Wagon wheels to tires and roads
turns to highways.
So, with that we had to adapt
against and do that.
I like to say employees try get
rid of us a handled years ago
where are they?
They are gone and we are here
I'm proud.
The same thing will happen now.
Just reasonable during covid.
We other largest affiliate of
team sners san francisco.
Most unions are demographic area
is larger.
We are the largest in san
francisco over all.
We have 5 locals that run
through here with jurisdiction.
There are like PRESIDENT Machine
man said 100,000 total within
the counsels.
And it gets confusing we are the
largest affiliate of teamsters
number one in san francisco.
Fast forward to the pandemic a
lot of people had essential
workers we did not.
We have ups, waste that is 20%
of make up we have shuttle
drivers, parking they went away
we lost 2,000 member in so
covid.
Some got laid off.
Some of us worked for free to
keep the local going.
We were at a point we were worry
body making payroll before we
were paid.
With dues.
What do we do?
Famous line we use and unions
supervisor chen which should be
aware we own agonize we
organize.
We are proud with my team I get
the credit and talk they do all
the work in the become grounds.
Will we organize the lodgist cal
scooters.
I'm back in work mode and I will
be straight we have this
problem.
I know amazon and folks are
sniffing around knocking on your
doors.
That's our next fight.
We will need the support of
everybody here you know they
said, they are saying now the
team sters care about jobs.
Our response is, da.
I mean -- with safety we care
about our jobs.
So, I want to give an example
of -- somebody born and raised
in san francisco I worked at
union square as a vallet.
Somebody would come in with
families and rent a car at rent
a car at the airport.
Teamster job.
They park at hotel or garage.
Can live here.
they are putting chargers in.
The spots the turnover and
vallet throw-4 times paid 25% 6
or 60 dollars.
These rain bows don't pay
anything no parking tax we'll
hit the folks.
How about the robo taxys pay
their share.
Why don't they pay the taxes?
I want to gnaw in your ear when
I come here you will see me
often I get two minutes you beat
me out.
I got that out I want to thank
you.
Thifrng my great staff and vice
PRESIDENT Carla.
And our office mark and business
aenltss and trustee.
The rest here yesterday I sent
them back to work.
Thank you I appreciate it.
Thank you.
[Applause].
>> all right.
Go to roll call.
New business is supervisor
dorsey.
>> submit.
>> thank you.
>> supervisor engardio.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk.
I want to honor the
extraordinary of life.
Suimportant we reflect on people
who quietly keep our city
running our neighborhoods are
cared for and streets are clean.
Sue was the people and did her
work with pride and joy.
Sue came to the united states
from vietnam in 1985 as a single
mother seek a better future for
herself and family inform 2012,
when she was in her early 60s
join the the d. Public works a
corridor worker on irving street
if 19th avenue to 24th avenue.
Day after day she cleaned the
sidewalk with pride and purpose.
Sheeen picked cigarette butts
out of the sidewalk cracks.
Everyone knew and loved her.
She was the spirit of san
francisco a city whereim
guarantees are not just part of
the fabric but the heart and
soul the every day heroes.
In honoring sue we honor what
san francisco stands for.
Refouj forim grant families
seeking a better life and a
place where we care for one
another.
Her legacy will continue to
inspire us all.
Thank you.
The rest I submit.
>> thank you, supervisor
engardio.
Supervisor fileder?
>> which item is this
>>
>> roll call for new busy.
>> speak after supervisor walon?
>> yes.
>> okay.
>> thank you.
Supervisor mahmood.
>> submit
>> thank you.
>> supervisor mandelman.
>> all right.
I have an in memory asking we
adjourn today's meet nothing
memory of daniel goldstein
passod the 20th at 74.
Born in mount vern an york.
Barb he graduate studies an fran
state university and
professional journey as a print
make are experiencing early
success with 2 d w.
A trendy studio in san francisco
gallery on fiveth in manhattan
am.
He had his show at brooklyn moou
museum.
In 1984 dannel was diagnosed
with hiv bh aids was a death
sentence made the decision to
devote years to sculptor.
After the death of his life
partner in 96 power like
structures with moving parts, he
created large executeors mostly
mobiles made from class, mesh
and medicine bottles for public
space.
Body of work displayed and
collected worldwide.
Two of his medicine man and
invisible man in the
international aids conference in
vienna.
An advocate for the aids
community founded and serve said
as board PRESIDENT Earning funds
to aids organizations.
The pedestrian visual aid
supports artists with illnesses
in the bay year.
Collections containing his work
found in the fine arts museum of
berkeley, art institute of
chicago [Speaking very fast]
Rest in peace MAY your memory be
a blessing and the rest I
submit.
>> thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
Supervisor melgar.
>> thank you, I have in memory
and I will be joining with
supervisor connie chan.
In supporting giving asking that
we close the meeting in the
memory offinea deerman passed
away left week at the age of 88.
She was the daughter of birtha
flemming the wife of interior
court justice john deerman and
mother of my friends kelley,
john and tracie.
Of course kelly being our
director of the department of
aging service.
Inea was the grand mother and
great grand mother and leaves a
long legacy of communities
service and service to our city.
She served on the san francisco
planning commission.
The landmarks preservation
advisory committee and devoteed
city, family and her community
in the fillmore.
Was a social worker by training
and a believe are in doing what
is right for all not just for a
few.
She advocated fiercely for more
open space.
Equal rights and for women's
rights.
She will be missed.
And I ask we close the meeting
in her memory.
And I know supervisor chan will
have a few words.
Thank you the rest I submit.
>> thank you supervisor.
>> that from the full board
theinea deerman.
And now -- gavelled we'll take a
break.
A break on roll call and gavel.
And then I will ask that our
clerk call the first of 3 P.M.
Special orders.
>> item 24 this is the board of
supervisors convening a
committee of the whole a public
hearing of the board today
JANUARY 28 for the members to
hear and respect updates on
progress and implementation
sttsz of united states
department of justice
recommendations.
Pertaining to reforms in the
police department.
All right.
Supervisor walton.
>> thank you, PRESIDENT
Mandelman.
I like to move that we continue
this item to the MARCH 18th 2025
board meeting.
Is there a second for that
motion?
Seconded by melgar.
And before we can vote we need
to take public comment.
MADAM Clerk, please, call for
public comment on the
continuance.
The board will hear public
comment on the continuance of
item 24 the update on findings
and recommendifications
pertaining to law enforcement
practices for this matter this
hearing to be continued to MARCH
18th, thank you.
If you are here to provide
comment on the matter step up.
We will take your public comment
on the continuance.
>> yes.
Move that away.
Now.
>> thank you.
Anyone else would like to
provide public comment.
Are you here to provide comment.
All right.
MR. PRESIDENT I dent see members
of public wanting to speak on
this merit
>> thank you, public comment is
closed.
Will colleagues we have a motion
to continue this hear to
merchandise 18 issue 25 board
meeting.
I think we can take that usual
call.
>> need a roll call
>> all right
>> on the motion to continue
item 24 to marijuana 18,
supervisor dorsey.
>> aye.
>> supervisor engardio.
>> supervisor fielder.
>> aye.
>> supervisor mahmood.
>> supervisor mandelman.
>> aye.
>> supervisor melgar.
>> supervisor sauter.
>> aye.
>> supervisor sherrill.
>> supervisor walon.
>> aye.
>> supervisor chan.
>> supervisor chen.
>> aye.
>> there are 11 aye's.
>> okay.
Without objection this hearing
is continued to MARCH 18, 2025.
>> MADAM Clerk go to our next
special order call 25-28
together.
>> yes.
Items 24-28 comprise the second
throw P.M. Special order for the
board to convene them is -- a
public hearing of persons
interested in the statute
exemption determination by the
planning department under the
california environmental quality
act issued on NOVEMBER 4 of 24
for the proposed mt amid
valencia curb side protected
bikeway protect implement
bicycle and pedestrian
improvements on valencia
relocating the rung bike lane on
valencia to curb side for
protected class 4 bike lanes
running from 15th to 23rd.
The proposed bike lanes ash
jaysent to the curb or wave
around the parklets it would
remove or relocate existing
parking spaceos some streets
that intersect to accommodate
existing bike share stations and
curb color designations.
26 the motion to affirm
planning's determination that
this project is statutely exempt
from environmental review.
Item 20 is the motion to
conditionally reverse the
planning determination and
subject to the adoption of
written findings and item 28 the
motion to direct a preparation
to reverse the determination.
>> thank you.
Colleagues, I own property
within a thousands feet of the
project and because that I have
been advise today best to recuse
myself.
With that I'm going to ask
walton to come up and preside
offer this part of the meeting.
Thank you, supervisor walon.
Thank you.
Colleagues I would like it
entertain a motion at this time
to excuse PRESIDENT Mandelman.
Made by supervisor chan and
seconded by supervisor fielder.
On the motion?
>> on the motion to excuse
xrierz mandelman from 2-28.
Supervisor dorsey.
>> aye
>> supervisor engardio.
>> aye.
>> supervisor fielder.
>> supervisor mahmood.
>> aye.
>> supervisor melgar.
>> supervisor sauter.
>> aye.
>> supervisor sherrill
>> aye
>> supervisor walon.
>> supervisor chan.
Why aye.
>> supervisor chen.
>> aye.
There are 10 aye's.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk
without objection PRESIDENT
Mandelman is excused.
Colleagues we have a hearing on
the appeal of the statute
exemption determination by
planning department for the
proposed mt amid valencia
protected bikeway project.
After the hearing the board will
vote whether to affirm or
conditionally reverse the
exemption determination for the
proposed project.
Without objection.
We will proceed as follows.
Up to 10 minutes for
presentation by the appellate.
Public comment 2 minutes per
speaker in support of the
appeal.
Up to 10 minutes for a
presentation from the planning
department.
Up to 10 minutes for mt a the
project experience.
Public comment 2 minutes per
speaker in opposition to the
appeal and finally up to throw
minutes for rebuttal by the
appellate.
I deponent see objections so we
will now open this public
hearing.
>> supervisor fielder do you
have anything you want to say
regards to this hear something
>> I will, I will have
questions likely for the
presenters but we can proceed.
>> thank you.
>> seeing no names I will now
ask the feel come forward and
present their case.
You have up to 10 minutes.
Thank you.
Mooim julio and represent the
peat in this matter.
The appellate is [Inaudible].
A community organization primary
low in the valencia corridor.
the issue specifically here is
twrop how mt a plans to proceed
in the development of the
valencia corridor and whether
ceqa and environmental impact
report is required or necessary
under the circumstances of this
project.
Contebldzs and I have here to my
left MR. David quinn bee that
the project is subject to two
exceptions.
One, that it impacts a
historical resource.
And two that the project in and
of itself and location has
unusual circumstances in play.
Now.
With respect to the historical
resources, valencia street has a
long history.
In many historical document it
is valencia is categorized the
first street of san francisco.
Of historical documents indicate
that valencia street was the
first street in san francisco
that was graded.
Valencia street is part of a
historic district.
The valencia 16 street post fire
And part of the liberty hill
historic district as well.
Nowhere in the submissions med
by the mt a thus far is there I
discussion of the impact that
the project with respect to the
bicycle lanes -- what so ever.
No discussion of what the
implications of the project will
entail to the corridor and
historic crawl and address in
our documents the aesthetics of
the street.
With the history of the valencia
street corridor one thing the
planning department has
highlight in the its studies is
that the commercial corridor has
value.
PRESIDENT Commercial corridor of
valencia has a proud history.
That the commercial corridor of
valencia is a very significant
entertainment and retail zone
for san francisco.
No one down thes that.
The focus of the project impacts
the character of valencia
street.
It is not addressed how the
impacts can be mitigate federal
at all.
Because they are not discussed.
No, the unusual circumstances I
think rely on the fact that the
street has a very long and
detailed historic contruck and
it is utilized at the current
time in ways that the
merchantses would contend is in
the at full capacity.
Post covid there has been a
downturn in businesses this have
maintained their presence within
the valencia commercial
corridor.
And the fact this this project e
eliminates more than 150 parking
spaces is of grave concern to
the commercial character of
valence why street.
There is an issue with respect
to the equity quity component.
Studies we submitted in
discussions and appeal indicate
that there is an equity
component with respect to
providing a lack of parking
spaces for person this is MAY
not be inclined to take public
transportation.
Or to utilize bikes to make
their purchases, visit or
otherwise engage in business
along the commercial corridor of
valence why street.
Disabled importance as we can
tell and from our experience
those persons have a problem
with the accessing of the street
currently because of the way it
is configured.
We contend those consideration
have not been taken in account
with respect to the mt a
submissions.
Importantly, we are talking
about people.
.
Talking about small business
persons this rely on valencia
for their livelihoods and rely
on it for their worth in
society.
That rely on it as guide posts
how they comport themselves in
the city family and the life.
And that currently, the mt a is
engage in the I process of
putting plans over people.
And -- that as a consequence of
this, the issues on have 11sia
will not be addressed in the
prerpt manner we do realize and
recognize well is a change in
transition taking place in san
francisco in the society and
general with respect to the way
people go from one place to
another.
At this points in time, it is in
the addressed.
I would like to ask MR. Quinnby
to step and up speak from the
heart as a merchants on that
corridor
>> hello I had living in the
mission for 30 scombroers small
business in san francisco for 35
years.
And I think we can agree you
heard about the valencia center
bike lane it was rolled out and
it really was a bit of a
catastrophe for small businesses
and others.
We just want things to be as we
progress -- all work together,
we want everybody to know what
is happening.
I walked around this weekend and
met with 200 merchantos the
valence why corridor many had no
idea this is happening.
You have to understand we are
all suffering from ptsd from a
pandemic a lot of people in the
room probably got did not have
to shut down and sit in the
corner for 3 years that's great.
You can work from home.
Small businesses can't.
We are like getting our sea legs
again and trying to kahl crawl
out they three this in front of
us that we all the sfmta did
their survey before the bike lin
was put inform 88% men cyclists
said no we don't want this.
Please issue don't do this.
They said we will do it anyway
and did it and we feel like we
are not heard.
I would say I feel like well is
a new day in san francisco.
We'll rise up.
I want to thank supervisor
fielder for spending half-hour
with us.
The other day.
Thank the mayor.
Who took two, one hour meetings
last tuesday and last night to
meet with all the stake holders
bike coalition.
Sfmta members.
We all want to work together we
ail love san pran and want a
better san francisco.
We get freaked out when the
environment in front of our
shops is changed.
I'm telling you if you roll out
a construction project and sfmta
does not have the best record on
staying on time.
I had another business on tear
very well.
suffered 6 years.
Now we have a ghost town.
Valencia street is a ghost town.
I didn't prepare I'm speaking
from the heart after 35 years
and -- I feel like the
polarization has been really
push the country apart.
And the state in the city.
And the fact that supervisor
fielder was willing to meet with
us and the new mayor met with
us.
It was fantastic and I think
there are a few here to speak to
their experience.
And mayor lurie we sat down in
the first thing he said like, I
will not tolerate demonization.
I said, silent I was like this
is how am.
I opened music venues so people
can listen to music.
Stop argue burglar politics and
the other things that media is
shoving down threes.
Thank you for your attention.
>> thank you so much.
For where you are presentation.
I don't see colleagues on the
roster for questions for the
appellate.
So, MADAM Clerk we'll go to
public comment specific low for
those withhold like to speak in
support of appeal.
And opposition to the project.
MADAM Clerk?
>> we are setting the timer for
two minute fist you would like
to speak on behalf of the
appellate step up.
>> only about [Inaudible].
The it is in the we are going to
reverse.
All the [Inaudible].
When are you going to wake up.
We will reverse that who will
pay for this?
They will undo when they do
mostly.
Keep one or two bike lanes.
End of the play here you are
done.
You are creating [Inaudible].
Buffer speak if would like to
speak lineup on the right side
of the chamber.
Welcome.
Thank you.
Am I'm betsy baron I own love
and lucks on valencia.
I have been in business there
for 15 years.
I lived and worked in the
mission for over 35 years.
I know the streets very well.
I also feel impacted by this
bike lane and all the
shananagans and the time we
spent meeting with mt a only to
feel steam rolled over.
I know there are other streets
that would be south end would be
a perfect street for the bike
lanes bet people downtown quick.
Not impact small business it is
large businesses on south van
ness and residents.
I think this turning valence why
to a wonderful place for bikers
serves a tiny demographic of our
city we have hills and families.
I hope that we can create a
corridor that is family friendly
and friendly to people with
disabilities.
Because they are over looked.
And our street has taken
longtory recover.
Than almost all the other
neighborhoods in the city.
I go to all the other
neighborhood its is vibrant.
People shopping excitement and
our street is sad.
So.
I would really like to be heard.
And have people understand the
gravity of what happened to us.
thank you.
>> next speaker, please.
>> hi I'm ema.
And I was here last time I'm
here again.
It should not be taken as any
type of indication that there
was unanimous approval left time
last time there was a ratio of
at least 30-1 expressed decent
for this new plan.
I think both merchants and
bikers are not happy with the
plan.
It takes away parking and make
its a wirfs upon experience for
bikers.
As a biker I want to say from my
perspective I think the most
important thing to make passing
save for different speeds of
bikers. And that's the thing in
the middle or there are
different ways my point is we
need to revisit the plan.
When there is 2 way traffic for
the bikers it makes it safer to
pass and as we have increasing
numbers of e bikes and scooters
there are all different speeds
of -- vehicles -- I have a fully
manual bike and it is heavy and
I have a 30 pound toddler and
her trail are I'm the slowest
moving bikeos that lane.
And there would be things
whizzing by me.
And I'm not opposed e bikes they
are the future and need to make
it safe for these e bikes to
exist and coexist with
traditional bikes.
But I really think the width of
the lane is what make its safe.
For different speeds of bikes to
share and bike around the city.
That's when we lose by to the
side we are losing park the
merchances can tell you about
safer for the different speeds
bikes and e bikes to share.
The advantage of having a two
way either all down the middle
or the side I don't care well
are ways we can do this.
It functions like a country road
with the dotted yellow line.
Thank you for your comments.
For those you have speaking just
look at the podium you will see
a timer on the podium.
You will know where you are in
your two millions
>> I'm [Inaudible] I have been
having [Inaudible] On valence
why for past 40 years.
I never seen ghost town before
on have 11sia just previous
gentlemen mentioned that.
I remember in 1992, I believe
the mayor said we be valencial
be north 90's and be all over
the newspaper.
But now in because of the
project this they did in the
middle of the street, not that
they made I race track for the
motorcycle biker they have a
heard time to bike in there.
They said than I will do this
for one year experiments and
cost million dollars.
According to cha I heard.
Now they made that for the biker
they made a race track.
Police have to the block each
intersection for them not to.
They are start being right at
the foreor 5 in the afternoon
and they are coming they hurt
the businesses driving down the
street is hard.
And left time I talked to a
couple of people from mt a they
had another meeting I told them
this is going to kill somebody
people they are riding the
middle and going to stop the
traffic lights are change.
And they have to stay there for
the few minutes before or 5 or
10 minutes before the next one
because the traffic will go so
slow and people they just make a
you turn in the middle.
I don't understand who is smart
idea was this and the smartest
idea to pass this.
Law?
I appreciate do something about
it and they said it is one year
experiment one million dollars.
And don't have money.
We don't have a budget.
I'm curtis a vet and at mission
pet hospital to have 11sia for
30 years.
Mission pet hospital been their
for 45 years.
The park next to us priority or
our needs have been there for a
year we have been there for 45.
They tomorrow the route of the
bike scomplan to me that is not
fair or based on the priors of
the board which should be
safety.
Not one of you came to my
business I never seen one of
you.
You are pre10ing like you
represent us you irrelevant
don't.
You don't represent any of us.
40 years of I business down the
drain.
You guys are ridiculous.
You guys think you are muchos
come down special see what is
going oi never seen you, you or
any of you.
Even my supervisor.
Took away my parklet.
500 dollar ticket for small rack
of clothing.
Give you tickets for [Inaudible]
You guys are bigger than
ridiculous.
Over 50 workers.
We need fauk about it?
really.
Go over there and look.
Nobody is there.
Helpful an hour every day for
ping.
Ping.
Ure think it is a joke!
Thank you for your comment.
Sir.
>> terry.
You had an opportunity to speak
at the podium.
Welcome to our next speaker
>> I'm sonia.
And I'm going to keep it short
my father in luhad a business on
valencia.
For 19 years and nothing
affected our business.
As much as the bike lane.
Since we lost about 40-60% in
business.
Every day I have customer
calling me telling me I can't
come in.
I vehicle looking for parking
the last 40 minute there is is
no ping we go somewhere else.
And I have been wing for 10 year
myself I know everybody and it
is sad to see my dad's business
go down so much just from bike
lane and it is in theeen a safe
bike lane I witnessed so many
hitting bicyclists making left
turn and u turns.
We all want safety and our
businesses to thrive.
We can't be taking away more
parking than we have been
taking.
Of of if you guys could see it
in your hearts to somehow make
things better.
Keep businesses going it is a
lively, fun street and sad to
see it be a ghost down.
Thank you for your time.
Thank you.
Welcome.
hello I'm sascha I have a new
business we are just 5 combleers
it OCTOBER.
San francisco forever.
Valence why from pretty crazy to
now.
It is a devastating thing to see
how chill it is.
Monday you come.
The street at mid day.
Dead.
Never was like that.
As a business owner I get
complaints from people prosecute
out of town.
Locals can't find park the spot
this is on 21st and valence why.
12 o'clock, full.
In order to get in you wit for a
car to come out it backs out.
They think this person is park
lead is parking there are for
the hell of it.
Back ups to valencia and then a
huge back up.
Takes one person toment to
crosswalk gets back you'd up to
past 22nd street.
Said people going in circles
looking for parking how is that
a benefit to the environment.
It is terrible.
Ef people out of town call we
don't want to in ping is
horrible.
You cannot find parking so --
not -- that affects businesses.
If I'm not knowing the sales tax
pace for this stuff.
How do you get sales tax we
can't have sales no onements to
come employs I have customers
that are handy cap they don't
want to come it is too
challenging.
This thing and you want to take
out more parking?
Are you trying to kill our
business this is is what san
francisco is made of mall
businesses.
Thank you for your time.
>> thank you.
>> I'm lisa.
Good afternoon.
Supervisors I live 5 blocks from
valence why ip a senior living
her for over 30 years.
Walking and bike I never owned a
car.
I had numerous close calls with
cars.
With a protected center bikeway
and I was even moreover joyed
with the idea of this improved
curb side protected bikeway.
Because as we saween with a
center protected bikeway the
accidents with people's bikes
the collisions dropped 20% with
the separated lanes.
I was looking forward to the
curb side protected lane it
offered more protection but it
offers cyclists an opportunity
to interact with merchances.
I love valencia street and -- as
people who remember the closures
of the two blocks was I have
brandt and people love having a
period of timeized for the
weekend.
I was actually like the world
class city we are we would have
period of timeized as many
people in europe did despite
being more populous.
I'm mark I came to peek on the
mayor's proposals concerning
homelessness and fentanyl but
because I heard this proposal
and I'm not from valencia I
wanted add a perspective you
have not head member we lived in
north beach for over 30 years.
Many strewns have business with
people who walk and in from out
of town.
And there say third group of
person clients.
people from noe valley or the
richmond we love to do that.
San francisco.
What the bike lane does and I'm
a bike rider can volcanize the
city.
Since the new bike lane is in
the search we gone to our
restaurant once.
And never gone back to that
neighborhood.
It is a decision we made.
Not casually my girlfriend is a
strong vegan and wonderful
restaurant I recommend it if you
can goat it.
It was too agis too hard for us
to get there easily for dinner.
Because of the bike lanes.
I'm offering a one person
perspective when it is like to
get on to valence why to be a
customer there we stopped going.
Good luck, thank you.
Thank you.
Good afternoon san francisco
supervisors a lot of new face.
I'd like to say happy lunar new
year.
I'm here not to talk about the
cars or bike lanes.
.
I'm here to talk about fentanyl.
This is only specific to people.
>> public comment.
Only for people who support
appeal.
Okay.
I believe that bike lanes
obstructed by people using
fentanyl is a detriment.
No its not you need to peek to
this appeal.
When I will be able to speak we
will have public comment at the
end of the meeting.
4.
.
20 I will sit down.
>> thank you.
mr. Decosta.
Supervisors.
This is san francisco.
And -- we look at it from the
point of you are the planning
department.
And the municipal transportation
agency which is one of the wirfs
agencies in san francisco.
Worse
franciscoworsemt
a cannot dot right out reach to
ask the business what is is it
they want?
The bicyclists with political
action committee worse it is all
about money, driving, grid and
destroying quality of life
issues worse I don't know who is
sitting down there if the
planning department or the mt
aor whatever worse let me tell
you san francisco is to used to
be a beautiful city worse
valencia street is a landmark
place worse the mt a ruined our
city worse tried dot same on san
bruno avenue worse thank you
worse
>> thank you worse next speaker
worse I'm [Inaudible] Worse I'm
taxi driver worse I go on
valencia street no left
[Inaudible] Worse [Inaudible]
[Inaudible] All the big
companies they can buy city with
money worse I want to you open
this lane on the side.
And help people and the taxi
drivers worse
>> thank you worse welcome
worse hello worse everybody
worse the valence why street
will drive tax when he we stop
for the passenger we start
getting honking and people yell
worse if this middle line was
not the bike lane the
[Inaudible] Parking they can go
around and we will up passenger
and take them temperature is
stress when you drive through
and pick update passenger from
valencia street it is very
difficult worse yea, better to
open it and onside for the bike
like a small side they go by and
everybody else is happy the
drivers are happy.
Passengerers happy worse now
believe me we are stress worse
when we get the honking we know
this person is in the from here
worse probably could do
something or do so we will get
creeped out.
Thank you worse
>> thank you worse are their
other peeshg who would like to
address the board regarding the
mid valencia bicycle curve side
bikeway project on behalf of the
appeal only worse MR. PRESIDENT
worse
>> thank you, no other
speakers public comment is
closed worse
>> now we will have it up 10
minutes for representatives of
the planning department worse I
believe we have lisa gibson and
jennifer mc keller worse
>> thank you worse good
afternoon acting PRESIDENT
Walton worse and members of
board worse I'm jennifer mc
keller.
>> speak in that microphone as
much as you can worse
>> okay worse if you can bends
the end it could reach taller
worse there you go worse
>> all right.
Is this better?
Thank you worse why sorry.
Good afternoon, acting PRESIDENT
Walon and members I'm jennifer
mc keller worse I'm a senior
environmental plan weir
planingly department.
with me is lisa gibson vipiral
review officer worse slide,
please.
Next slide.
Our presentation will include a
summary of the project and our
key responses to the appeal
worse which include, firming
department's fining the project
qualifies for an exemption worse
explaining the difference with
an exemption and categorical
exemption worse legal standard
of review for a statute ory
exemption met all local
notification and conclude width
department's recommendation to
the board regarding the appeal
worse the project site consists
of 8 block segment of valence
why street worse the project
remove an existing 2 way center
bikeway and replace with a curb
side class 4 bike lane on each
side worse the project would
moist location and number of
spaces for park.
Loading, park and bike shares
went segment to accommodate the
side running bike lanes worse
the department has provide
findings in the seck wa
qualifies for an exemption
ourndz section 2108 twr 25 known
as sustainable transportation
project exemption worse these
are summarized on the slide and
our response memo.
Appellate did in the challenge
these findings worse as an aside
this exemption created by state
lgdz enact in the 2020 and 2021
both coexperienced by former san
francisco supervisor scott
wiener worse the exemption
createed stream line
environmental review for public
transportation and bike and
period of time infrastructure
projects that reduce car
dependsancey the appellate
mistaken it forical cal
exemption they MAY sounds
similar they have key
differences.
The project is eligible for
statute ory exemption if fits
specify in the the exemption
worse similarly, a project is
eteligible for aical exemption
if fits any of the class types
described in the ceqa
guidelines.
For statute ory exemptions no
requirement for vipiral impacts
unless it spes fies worse in
contrast project this is qualify
are presumeed not sulin
environmental affects and
environmental impacts must be
occurred eligibility.
A project is not eligible for an
exemption if any of the
exceptions specified apply worse
they include factors such as
project location, cumulative
impact.
Affect due to unusual
circumstances and potential low
significant impacts to historic
resources.
Where as a statute ory exemption
there are no exceptions that
must be considered worse these
differences greatly lim the
grounds upon which a challenger
can attempt it defeat the use of
a statute ory exemption compared
to a calgarial worse the
agencies finding based on fact
worse assumptions predicated
upon facts and expert opinion
supported by facts worse in
addition, courts defer it agents
decision based on substantial
evidence worse by contrast, the
fair argument standards of
review applies to categorical
exemption evidence support a
fair or reasonable argument a
project MAY result in
environmental affects a higher
level of -- environmental review
is required even if there is
contradicting evidence that know
significant impact would result
worse where it applies the court
are less00 argues the department
required conduct public
notification and out reach
during the environmental review
press worse ceqa does in the
require public noteification or
out reach during the vieshthal
review qualified unless specify
instead exemption.
This exemption does in the
require public notification or
oust roach for project this is
cost less than 50 million
dollars worse since the project
would cost less than that up to
2. 5 million dollars no public
notification or out reach during
environmental review period is
required worse the department
has met all ceqa and local
chapter 31 of the code
requirements.
Including posting the ceqa
determination to the exemption
website.
The ceqa determination was site
instead sfmta board of directors
hearing packet and resolution at
the time of project approval.
To conclude the department
recommends tht board of
supervisors uphold the
department's determination the
exemption conforms with the
requirements of ceqa and deny
the appeal worse the department
provides evidence of the project
of exempt from environmental
review under ceqa on the basis
it meets the definitions and all
applicable criteria in ceqa
worse the department also
satisfied all ceqa in chapter 31
of the code requirements worse
the appellate not demonstrated
the department ceqa was not
supported by substantial
evidence worse thank you for
your time we are available to
answer quests that you MAY have.
>> thank you worse do we have
questions for planning?
Supervisor fielder worse
>> I want to you00 eye believe
covered this but can you
reiterate in plain terms why the
project does not require the
environmental impact report?
Meets everything in the
exemption under ceqa sections
worse that's not lyman's terms
but -- basically, just to
simplify it statute ory
exemptions don't require an
analysis of environmental impact
unless it is specifically stated
in this statute ory exemption
worse that's what is the
difference from categorical
exemptions
>> can you give context as to
sb922 and the purpose of this
statute ory exemption was?
>> the purpose is to promote
sustainable transportation worse
>> understood worse thank you
worse
>> and -- the appellate argues
that the bikeway project impact
on a historic district.
And this there has been
inadequate public involve am.
Can you explain if they apply
here and why or why not.
This statute ory exemption has
public notification and out
reach requirements however only
for projects over 50 million
dollars worse this project which
come in at up to 2.5 million
dollars, none of the public out
reach and notification
requirements are applicable to
it worse
>> understood.
And the impact on historic
district?
Can you explain.
Kwo
>> since it qualify for statute
ory exemption not required
evaluate impacts environmental
impacts including those to
historic resources.
>> okay worse thank you worse
>> thank you worse supervisor
dorsey
>> thank you.
PRESIDENT Walton worse so my
reading of this case and tell me
if I'm geting right it seems to
me this turns entirely worse on
whether well is a legal bases
for this appeal begin state law
provides for a starch ory
exemption for bike lanes worse
if this is a project for bike
lanes if yes it is exempt.
If meets all criteria.
More than just is it -- bike or
pedestrian projects.
>> okay.
>> I will MAY be just to
guidance in my view.
Made about the bike lanes what
was before us here, is whether
there was adequate environmental
review worse and I'm going to
confess that few thing in my
career irritated me more than
watching california's
environmental protection law
ceqa, weaponize against
environmental priorities.
That was what the legislator did
when they passed sb288 governor
newsom sign today in law worse I
want to keep an open mind but
what I hear is this is a bike
lane project worse it is statute
oref exempt worse I have not
heard anything yet, I understand
people have different views well
is a policy airport I'm
interested in hearing worse but
I have not heard anything that
will convince me this is
requires review worse there is
what the legislator sought to
address and I will say -- 20
years ago there was a case the
coalition for adequate rerue.
Car versus san francisco that
stymied our bike lane project
for years worse it was
frustrating that was the
legislator sought to address
worse we should not be back with
this worse I would be interested
to hear on rebuttal is is this
exempt or not worse I'm not
worse
>>
>> thank you worse supervisor
dorsey worse
>> I don't see other questions
from colleagues so worse we will
callum representatives from mt a
the project responsibles I
believe we have paul and jen and
he victoria wise.
>> thank you, and good
afternoon supervisors I'm paul
I'm the sfmta project manager of
the mid valencia project worse
I'm here to provide a brief
context on work on the valencia
corridor the issues this we have
seen on the corridor worse are
rung bikeway pilot.
And side running curb side bike
lane as well worse I want to
start with a summary of work
including the transportation
safety trinlds on the corridor
before covid and our project
goals that we kept in mind since
the beginning of our work worse
we thought a lot about valencia
the last 25 years worse the
first bike lanes were stripe in
the 1999 worse in 2010 sidewalk
widening 4 black section in the
middle worse a year before covid
a side running protected bikeway
on the northern section worse
and about to dot same for the
middle section when the pandemic
started worse worse when we
picked it up again in 2022 the
priorities of valence why
changed worse and the best fit
for upgraded bikeway that
addressed the safety occurrence
was a bikeway worse a year ago
the center running design was
not working for everyone worse
and sfmta board of directors
instructed the team to
investigate pivot to a side
running curb design that design
was finalized based on
collaboration and out reach in
the stake holders along the
corridor and approved by our
board late last year worse
>> that's a bit about the
history of work.
I did want to talk about the
characteristic of valencia
especially when it come to how
people use the street worse we
thought about valence why and
ways to improve min tang the
character on the street worse it
is amaze with vibrant shops,
night life, stores and cultural
centers and a popular bike route
and 35 huh human a day use it to
shop, commute and visit worse it
it is in the worse provides
direct connections between
neighborhoods streets to the
west so gerrero or delores are
car focused.
The west are transit focused
like mission worse streets in
between don't connect the
southern neighborhoods to market
worse unfortunately valence why
on the high injury network 12%
of streets that account for 68%.
Severe collision in san
francisco worse between 2015 and
19, 2 cyclists a month are
struck by vehicles on the
corridor of valencia worse
riding bikes was challenging
with kettle cut off and side
hits from vehicles worse trucks
blocked the bike lane to load or
grab something from a store
worse I mentioned before with
this in minds we wanted improve
sense of safety and
protectability for pedestrians
and cyclists in this corridor
and approached these with 3
goals in minds. First was to
improve safety for everyone who
traveled there worse we want to
preserve or enhumans the
corridor and wanted improust
conscience society movement of
goods and peopled be save and
predictable worse I mentioned we
selected a new design for the
corridor like to briefly discuss
what we landed in a center
running design and when we
learned from public engagement.
After covid we wanted start
designing and improve bikeway
for the middle section between
15 and 23rd worse 70 parklets
were out door dining areas, curb
side loading for food deliver
and he parking spaces to small
business worse in 2023 a
standard bike we was implemented
it was new but, loud for all
parklets to remain against the
curve.
Of and yukted bikeway that
addressed the side swipes and
people in the bikeways
>> after we heard a lot.
Some at the time they were not
sure when and where than I could
park.
The ability to double work was
taken away.
We heard that businesses were
struggling with covid worse we
heard center running lane
improve am from the previous
wron worse cyclists visibility
and safer and ride was
predictable.
Some felt when emergency
response vehicles people on 4
wheelers use it it was
disruptive worse final designs
in SEPTEMBER attended by 2 huh
human people worse and after
this, we had our final design
worse the final design
considered all of the design
constraints up and down the
trade offense out reach and
feedback and project goals.
Final design optimizes per
parking, loading, emergency
services and access, better
sight lines with motorists and
pedestrians and cyclists worse
parklet, motor scooter parking
and increase in accessible blue
zones worse and incoming the
accessible blue zones worse the
final project approve bide our
board in NOVEMBER of left year
we have 40 people showed up and
spoke on the project worse or
against worse and considering
how to best implement it since
then worse our out reach did not
stop during plan and design
worse we held valencia working
group meetings with residents,
small businesses issue ordinance
and stake holders to better
understand what work and did not
the last time.
In out roach we heard to avoid
construction during winter
holiday season.
One we will request and honor
worse we partnered with public
work who is the assist in
construction worse repave the
center to make sure we don't go
back and fix potholes and the
actual side running bikeway
design worse construction last
2-3 months we are doing it
through the rainy season. And
fully red to start as soon as
possible worse with that said,
thank you for your time and
project team and I are available
for questions worse thank you
worse thank you.
Supervisor fielder worse there
are specific construction
activities we will give notice
ahead of time worse and then --
is there anything else we are
doing?
We're planning open for business
marketing campaign worse we
understand this owning a small
business is challenging and want
to make sure the ordinance are
supported.
Thank you.
Thank you worse do we have other
colleagues with questions?
Welcome our first speaker worse
I'm erin worse I'm a bicyclist.
Public transis ride and driver
worse
when I choose to bike I'm
choosing an environmentally
friendly option.
It is not the safest choice
often.
Bicyclists in the room are
fightingly hard for a protected
bike lane because it is I matter
of our life or death.
That's it life our death.
The -- when I took the mart city
cycling class I learned to bike
on streets without bike lanes or
protected or unprotected lines
the advice is often to fully
roadway in the lane like a car
or minimum outside of the door
zone a deadly feature of streets
there is no separation with
parked vehicles and bicyclists.
So I don't get killed.
when I roadway in this safe way
I'm intimidated by cars.
I have been why would at and
tailgated on bryant street the
only place I feel safe to bike
is on have 11sia.
Protected bike lanes are my life
line.
The data shows that protected
bike lanes the standard of
safety for all road users.
I the controller's office report
indicated there was.
Thank you for your comment.
Thank you.
>> welcome, next speaker,
please.
Why hello I'm joe anna I live in
d 8 not for from valencia
street.
I'm a member of the san
francisco sierra club executive
committee and board of the
bicycle coalition.
I served as administrative law
judge over ceqa case including
multimodal transportation
projects that incorporated
bicycle infrastructure.
I am speak nothing my personal
capacity only.
I'm not here to talk about the
merits of one design or another.
Ip here to punishment effective,
fortunate governors thatup holds
the rule of law and delivers
results quickly.
In this case the luis open and
shut.
Proper procedures were followd
and a statute exemption applies.
I encourage to you vote to deny
the appeal because that's what
the law dictates and move on
from this discussion so this
gentleman can spend its limited
time and resources on other
pressing questions like funding
muni.
I want to note that I hear that
the merchants who spoke have a
lot of concerns about parking
management.
Parking management cross the
city is an issue.
And it deserves a deeper look.
There are many ways to implement
parking management including in
ways compatible with and
complimentary to a safe bike
network.
But exploring parking management
is separate matter from the ceqa
exemption that applies here.
Please, denight appeal.
Thank you.
>> next speaker, please.
Good afternoon.
Supervisors zack.
I live near valencia corridor
and travel on it frequently I'm
asking you to reject the appeal.
It is exempt under sb9 twoochl
the appellate is giving you 189
pages of material and not one
provides rational where the
exemptions don't apply here.
Appellates misstate the legal
standard.
The planning department explains
an exemption aplies if evidence
the project meets the criteria.
This is the case here this is a
bicycle facility.
In the public right-of-way and
carried out by local agency.
Meeting labor requirements.
Appellates base argument on a
fair argument standard does in
the apply to a statute ory
exemption.
Lusays this has no merit.
This pel is happening the
community told the city the
center running design is in the
working for them and staff works
to prosecute pose a new design
that respondeds to as many
priorities as possible in a
constrained space offer out
reach, meetings, open houses.
Noticers and mailings a hearing
before the sfmta board that is
gentleman ws to get this done.
Guaranteeing this appeal mean we
are stuck with the current
design for long are something
this nobodiments.
I ask you reject this pel to
allow installation to move
forward and further prioritize
completing the protected bikeway
so we can have safety on the
corridor.
Thank you.
>> thank you.
Welcome.
Next speaker, please.
>> good afternoon.
Supervisors I'm claire and I'm
director for the san francisco
bicycle coalition I'm here on
behalf of our members in the
bike community to ask you reject
the appeal before you today.
Valencia is one of the most
highly used corridors for people
on bikes as transportation in
the city.
It statute main artery
connecting people to the
corridors like market, 17th and
san jose avenue and cannot be
moved a parallel street.
Bike communitiment said to see
businesses thrive export to work
with the city to support
customer dover's recovery.
Through the mid valencia project
people biking the hop off bike
and enter upon business in a few
feast new lane.
In the last 5 years staff
exhausted so much time and
resources connect the most
exspencive out reach we have
season to create the project.
This work was presented at the
NOVEMBER 19 board of directors
where they approved it.
construction on the project was
supposed to start at beginning
of the year and the appeal is
delaying that.
Exempting transportation
projects from ceqa means we
implement life saving and
environmental friendly
interventions faster and cost
effectively.
Thank you.
Next speaker, please.
>> good afternoon.
I'm matt bigger my family exit
live nothing the can have the
row for 20 years.
Not for if the corridor.
I ask you oppose the appeal
today.
The protected bikeway went
through a public planning
process.
And unanimous low approved by
the sfmta board of directors
last year.
Granting would [Inaudible]
Democratic process and hinld are
actions on safety road users.
90% by bike and 33 bus I have
also driven dp found parking in
near by garages.
Research shows well plan said
infrastructure support I have
better than business customer
dovers reflect in the the
controller's report last year
the bike lanes not the reason
for decline in post ban pandemic
businesses I understand yet
center running lanes MAY not
helped in bringing back business
the approved curb side protected
lanes like those found arnold
the world allow biking and
scooting to stop and p at
businesses along the street.
Valencia has been a key corridor
for people on bike and
transportation for decades and
the curb side protected bikeway
will make it safe and supporting
easy access to local businesses
go forward for these reasons and
others and not stopped or
delayed.
Based on environmental appeal
that runs counter to luand harms
rather than protects the
environment.
Oppose the appeal and stop the
delay on this project for
people's safety and vibrancy of
neighborhood, thank you.
Thank you.
>> good afternoon will
supervisors.
I'm patrish why george a member
of the bike coalition I live in
d 9.
I roadway my bike down valencia
to go to doctor's appointments.
Shopping and different
activities.
I am here to ask to you oppose
the appeal before you today.
You heard there was a lot of
public planning process going on
prior to this decision that was
med in NOVEMBER.
And the mid ra11s why project
meets the requirements for the
exemption.
Safety should be our primary
concern here.
The rate of bike collisions
dropped 20% with installation of
separated complains go become to
unprotected with the
devastating.
Lives are at risk if a person is
injury have had in I bicycle
there MAY not be able to work.
And if you are older like me,
your chance of a fracture and
disability is higher.
I don't own a car I walk, biker
take public transit oppose the
appeal before you, thank you
very much.
>> thank you.
next speaker, please.
Hello.
I'm adam and I'm a long time
resident of san francisco and
member of the bike coalition but
here as a father.
Father of bike commuter with 2
young kids for me safety is a
priority.
I robbery following the project
now for years.
And part of some of the out
reach they have done it is clear
they have done tremendous out
reach.
Entires dorsey hit it on the
head when we are talking about
we north here to relitigate or
whether parking or economic that
stuff is important but that is
not what the issue hereby.
I ask you to vote on the merits
and asking to you oppose the
appeal.
Thank you very much.
Good afternoon.
My wife could not here I took
time off work.
We visit valencia street and
regular patrons to the
businesses we cycle or walk to
valencia.
If safe bicycle lanes were
removed or car traffic made it
less safe we would not be able
to patronize the businesses we
love.
We love valence why and
businesses but have to
prioritize our safety of courses
you urge you to oppose the
appeal.
Thank you.
Welcome.
Depend afternoon I'm sustainable
transportation in the city.
And this is a legal issue.
Ceqa creates the exemption.
That's when we are hear to side
noto relitigate the design of
the bikeway the question of is
this project exempt.
Sb922 recognized safety should
not be up to a veto.
We deserve safe facilities.
I want to give know example of
where this city has upon fund
ceqa appeals to delay progress
this is gary boulevard.
Fought a 40 year battle for
sustainable vipirally friend low
public transportation that was
fortunate starting as ln an lrv
plan.
Then a brt.
It was not until the exemption
to ceqa review came in affect
the city was able to paint a red
complain speedup the bus on
gary.
If we approve this appeal we go
back to the years where people
put an nel for every street
change and don't have time for
that we are facing budget
deficits we must move quickly
and an efficient transportation
system this means the exemptions
are central.
I'm here to ask you to reject
the appeal the MR. Presidenting
department has a summary
explaining why the valence why
project questions of law foils
for bounded efficient
environmental review.
The sfmta completed prior to the
approval in NOVEMBER.
Despite not required to, frankly
the sfmta staff put together
hundreds of hours of community
engagement for the most
processes we seen an
infrastructure project in the
city.
The code is clear this it appeal
need to decided on legal merits
and does not aline with state
law.
People read the numbers a bit.
active transportation projects
like this one are exempt from
environment will review because
they improve bicycle safety.
And the city street safety and
transportation goals including
vision zero goals.
I'm asking to youup hold the
law.
Reject the appeal and let
project move forward.
Thank you.
>> next speaker, please.
>> hello I'm speak nothing my
own capacity.
Excite to see the new
supervisors here.
Great new board.
I want to thank new supervisor
fielder for leadership o this
top and I can work for
sustainable transportation and
upon climate action over all.
I urge to you reject the peel
and I think supervisor dorsey
put it let reasons why this
appeal is misguided.
I realliment to praise sfmta
staff.
And the w than I do and out
reach I seen on this project and
others the pin they go to
walking door to door to ensure
that.
The stake holders are, wear and
have opportunity to ask
questions.
And I wanted to call out the
detail the planning staff
explained the exemption.
I think that the work that the
public servients do is not easy
temperature is so critical.
It is under appreciated often
faces criticism and this is I
case policies aside they really
deserve appreciation for that
work.
I urge you to reject the appeal.
>> thank you for sharing your
comments.
Next speaker, please.
>> hello thank you for aim to
make our streets safer.
I live admit mission I bike and
take public transit.
The valencia lane gives meet
freedom to travel without a
vehicle.
I know in the everyone bikes
since I'm not driveingly I'm
leaving the road traffic free
and parking open anyway.
It would be a disgrits fitook up
a precious parking spots this
some people need.
Least bike lane in place so
those who don't need a car can
stay carless.
Most people stated it seems
parking is the issue here and
not the bike lane.
Call it what it is a parking
issue and in the a bike lane
issue.
Why not stop allowing people to
store cars all the over the
vehicles that move every
thursday morning for street
weeping and used once or twice a
month.
Seems a better bike lane is the
solution to the ping problems we
are tacking about.
Thank you very much.
>> thank you.
Just so we are clear.
>> on behalf of the sfmta
>> yes, ma'am
>> my apologies for
interrupting you I did in the
know we were talking about bikes
and cars.
Bikes and cars.
Near longest time I never had a
car I was beak I hated an occur.
Now I have a car and concerned
about the bicyclists.
And I think I speak for the
major of san francisco when i
say, there are a lot of people
passionate about cars here and
passionate about bicycles here.
My uncle started me's diner,
american graffiti there are
american classic cars use in
this movie and people passionate
about cars.
I knowledge you spoke on behalf
of the appeal?
You spoken on behalf of the
appeal.
Thank you.
Hear from the next speaker.
Welcome.
I'm janet I live in d 9 and
voted for supervisor fielder.
Thank you.
I very much hope you will dot
right thing here and reject this
appeal.
It is -- .
S ceqa to feel person thing this
is dem creditally we want now
made it possible to say ceqa
does in the apply let us follow
his law and not let ceqa prevent
this from going forward.
I'm concerned that you heard
over from people wlo
representative a small fraction
of the affected population who
care about the bike lane.
I'm not a member of
organizations that people have
represented here I'm a regular
citizen.
I -- want to represent other
regular citizens who can't come
to the meetings and say, yes we
part of the people the mt a
interviewed and asked and we
want the bike lanes and do want
to feel safer in our
neighborhoods andment to walk
safely and bike safely.
Thank you.
>> thank you.
Next speaker, please.
>> I'm edward I want to thank
you for being here and taking
your time and provideingly the
forum for people to speak out.
I want to summarize had people
said before am the mall
merchants on the corridor since
1967.
I have been fortunate it allowed
me to chronicle what valencia
has been like for the last 58
years.
We talked about 1905 and talk
about 1970.
I am a racer I love bikes.
But we have to strike a balance
on valencia we comprised largest
corridor of inspect small
businesses that rely on vehiclor
traffic and bicycles.
If safety is a concern I'm with
you.
Post a slow are speed limit.
If you are under -- in the 2030
miles per hour range that would
be a cheap are alternative that
recondition figure the streets
and designs.
No offense to the mt a your
heart is in the right place and
the work was well thought out
and planned.
It did in the necessarily
provide for a fluid flow of
traffic and caused problems and
that's why oui are here.
Getting back to that is really
person that we all learn to
coexist and live together
perhaps a slower speed limit
might be an option.
This is public comment for those
on behalf of the project.
Welcome to our next speaker.
>> good afternoon my name is
damion I use the bike lane daily
I'm here to support the
rejection of the appeal.
It sounds like a lot of
opposition is based on the
economic affects of bike lane.
which I can't peek to but to me
it seems like a scapegoat for
other issues.
I feel for the the small
business ordinance I don't think
the bike lane is the bigef
issue.
In their you know problems.
Thank you.
>> thank you.
Of next speaker, please.
Welcome.
Hello.
Good to see you all.
Good afternoon supervisors I'm
customer an far I'm a dad that
live in d 9 with my family.
Congratulations supervisor
fielder for joining the
district.
I empathize with both sides.
I used to be a taxi driver.
Now I'm a small business owner.
And I'm an elected leader of the
sierra club.
I'm speak nothing my own
capacity.
I appreciate the occurrence here
export to speak to park nothing
a second I have to say this is a
cut and dry ceqa exemption in
the a lot of merit to discuss on
the project itself.
This is clear exempt under sb922
and ask you to oppose the
appeal.
All that said, I understands the
parking concerns and prepandemic
I worked for the northeast
parking improve am project that
has been put on hold by the mt
a.
And I think that would be one
way to mitigate these challenges
that alost mall businesses
raised by using that plan the
residents came up with to
provide parking capacity for the
northern district mission
district.
happy to work with your office
on that.
Thank you all.
>> thank you for sharing your
comments.
Welcome.
Hello I'm robyn pam I lead
[Inaudible] Streets that are
safe enough for kids it walk and
bike you ufrm to you move
forward on the project today.
Appealers necessary it is
delaying a project that has
community support and meets the
exemption standards as many have
detailed already.
The.
Sfmta conducted public out reach
for this next phase of the bike
lane they spent the left year
engage with merchants and the
community.
I have been involved in bike
lane projects in san francisco
this is more resources for
public out reach I have seen on
any project by prebl a factor of
throw or 5.
And this is 8 blocks of one
street.
We have an entire city of
streets that we need to make
safe.
So, not everyone aggress on the
outcome this level of effort the
agency under taken we flecks it
is fairness of the press.
The delays via appeals and
litigation that are possible are
unfair to the people who did
engage in good faith to find
real solutionos complicated
streets.
And it really only postpones
addressing the public safety
issues impact the neighborhood.
We talked to merchants and a
result of work we have done the
past year when we hear is
that -- the issue are that the
streets are not clone or people
don't feel safe walking to the
cars at 2 A.M. On the street.
I think there is like this a
trpgdz project.
It can solve transportation
safety.
It can't solve all the prospects
in the neighborhood.
So.
I think what we're asking for
fruas leaders is reject the
appeal and w to address the
issues that are hampering the
recovery of small business
corridors citywide.
>> thank you for your comments.
>> welcome to our next speaker.
Skwoo I'm a small business owner
on valencia.
I do believe that -- the side
running is the safest thing I'm
very shocked to hear none of the
people speaking of motorized
bicycles.
Riding up and down the same
narrow bike lanes.
That is a safety issue if you
are on muscle power I'm
concerned about the
implementation we have seniors
in the city walk with canes.
They need a chance to be able to
combh out and enjoy the
corridor, too.
.
And the fact that what little
park that is going to be left
will be handed over to the
delivery culture.
Over entitled neighbors which
sounds like the bike coalition
is has been invaded like the
democratic committee of people
that are not here for san
francisco.
They have little investment in
san francisco except for
speculation.
If you are concern body safety
why have you not addressed
motorized bicycles in the same
lane as regular bicycles.
I agreed I was assured there
would be more parking available
to handy capped people.
For hundreds of parking places
that are just for learning
delivery.
>> delivery culture not are you
supporting the project.
>> yes.
I we need to get rid of this
bike lane that does in the mean
we have to destroy the mission.
>> you are speaking in favor but
I'm concerned about
implementation and you
supervisors are responsible to
all of san francisco.
Not just the bike coalition who
young and healthy.
>> thank you.
>> hello.
I'm in the mission.
[Inaudible].
I have propose the the pel to
the bike lane.
An amazing job of public out
reach.
I was impressed with the level
of contact with the community.
I thought that was [Inaudible]
For this process.
I also user of the center bike
lane I like I'm happy they are
trying new alternate I was there
is a lot of traffic on valence
why but the best way to reduce
is provide good alternatives to
driving and safe bike lane does
achieve that.
Thank you.
Oppose the, thank you.
Before the next speaker are
there other members ever public
who would like to address the
board on behalf of the project
or the project experience?
step up behind terry field.
Welcome.
Sir.
>> thank you.
>> hello board.
Pardon my appearance I came from
a swim lesson from my child.
The appeal before you has has
legal merits.
It falls in the exemptions
established by bill 922.
As it is for pedestrian and
bicycle facilities improve
safety, access or mobility.
Reject the appeal.
Sfmta can begin construction of
the bikeways that will make the
streets safer and better for
business and help more shift to
bikes.
In addition to the categorical
exempt from ceqa the design bike
ways increase safety for all
including car drivers, revenues
for businesses and help shift
from cars.
This new design will help our
cities recover and helping to
address the road safety crisis
and climate crisis and reduce
noise and air mrougz and
improving quality of life and
public health e sfl for people
who live near were by valence
enthusiasm the design has been
gone through public out roach
with people after 6 plus years
of related work by stay stay 8
block stretch and construction
working group by the sfmta
including merchants and
residents agreed on construction
start nothing early JANUARY.
Which was delight
ayed by this appeal
I urge to reject the appeal.
Thank you.
>> thank you.
MR. PRESIDENT.
>> thank you public comment.
>> did not speak in support of
peel is closed.
>> you can't speak on both
items my apologies.
Seeing no speaker public comment
on is closed.
The appellate will have rebuttal
for 3 minutes.
Skwoo too address the legal
point.
The way the statute ory
exemptions work traditional low
urn california law if the
project was related existing
facilities, whether minor in
nature.
And it could be reasonably
construed it did not have
environmental impacts.
The statute supported and
sponsored by supervisor past
supervisor wiener specifically
addresses the bike lanes.
However, in isolation that
project and the way the statute
must be construed is this type
of project favors the
environment.
Improves the environment.
Is a positive factor for the
environment.
And in this case the public
testimony on behalf of the
appellate and the submissions
made in show of that a
reasonable argument base on the
evidence of the public testimony
that was made today that the
project has environmental
impacts of a negative character.
Specifically associated with a
historic property, historic
region of san francisco.
And there is no mention in any
submissions made on the city and
the mt a that addresses that
specific point.
And -- that is the contention on
a legal matter.
>> I would like to put on the
record that there was a lot of
out reach the final plan was not
unveiled until we met at the
chapel late assessment.
So when we were asking could we
see the what the layout they
said no you can't see.
We could not see it and it was
cloak in the mystery.
And then around almost OCTOBER
first, they show today to us.
Our only chance to talk and I'm
glad we did I love speaking with
meeting everybody, we want a
better city this has been
constructive.
But we had OCTOBER to understand
what would happen and how tell
affect everybody including
cyclists and we and the holidays
happened.
This was the only way to get
together and talk.
We proposed other streets and
yea I think that is it we I'm
glad everybody came together to
speak on this we just -- had
about 5 weeks to digest the
information and most are okay
with the center bike lane and a
lot of for now I think
bicyclists would like changes
the new, thanks.
>> thank you so much.
And now that will we heard if
all parties this public hearing
hen held and now filed.
As previously discussed we will
now consider whether to affirm
or reverse the exemption
determination for the proposed
project.
Supervisor fielder.
>> thank you.
Right now PRESIDENT Walten.
As this appeal occurrence my
district I prepared remarks.
I want to confirm it my clothes
and everyone today I have met
about both the appellates and
the experience of the sfmta and
planning.
As well as others and merchannel
groups interested in this
appeal.
Although I assumed office a few
weeks ago and as a resident of d
9 I have been, wear of the
issues facing valencia street
and the various iterations of
the of bikeway.
Include the serious occurrence
around pedestrian cyclists and
commuter safety and the economic
struggles of the vibrant small
businesses.
The question before us today is
not to consider the merit was
proposed bikeway project itself.
That was populared approved last
NOVEMBER after hearing throw
hours of public comment.
I want to reiterate that why we
are here is not at the
initiation of the board it it is
at the increase of the
appellate.
To be clear.
I carefully reviewed the appeal
materials and the departmental
responses discussed with the
city attorney and confirm the
question before us is a very
narrow question.
Of weather mt a proposed curb
side bikeway project falls under
the statute or exemption
determined under ceqa.
So, we are here today to
consider the planning
department's decision to find
that statute ory exemption under
ceqa section 2108025 should be
upheld.
When projects fall in the
exemption the question is not
whether they will or MAY have
impact.
Whether they fall in the scope
of the exemption.
as laid out in planning response
letter dated JANUARY 17, 2025,
as well as it is eligibility
check list on NOVEMBER 4 of
2024.
Include as exhibit a orb page 15
of the appellate's letter.
Planning was bound by the
definitions and criteria set
forth in ceqa section.
Of as we heard from planning.
The purpose of the exemption in
circumstance b922 which was to
improve public transit, biking
and walking infrastructure with
projects exactly such as those
in mind.
As I said to all the groups I
met with about this appeal and
I'm reiterating today I'm
committed to working with
merchants and our bike
pedestrian transit advocates to
continue to improve continues.
And all of d 9.
Because as we know the issues
are not.
At all limed the bikeway.
But extend to public safety,
economic revilingization and
continuing to message that the
mission district and valence why
are safe, vibrant and enjoyable
community spaces.
I encourage the sfmta to
continue to be engaged with our
small businesses in the
community throughout this
process.
As we heard today and before,
the stakes are too high.
And valencia merchants and or
corridor deserves the city's
support from start to finish.
With all that said, colleagues I
would like to make a motion to
affirm the determination by
planning that the proposed
valencia bikeway project is
exempt from environmental
review.
I move to adopt item 26 and
table 20 and 28.
>> thank you.
We have a second to that motion
by supervisor dorsey.
>> MADAM Clerk on the motion.
>> yes.
On the motion to approve item 26
and table 20 and 28 supervisor
dorsey.
>> aye.
>> supervisor engardio.
>> supervisor fielder.
>> ayech
>> supervisor mahmood.
>> aye.
>> supervisor melgar.
>> aye
>> supervisor sauter.
>> supervisor sherrill.
>> aye.
>> supervisor walton.
>> supervisor chan.
>> aye.
>> supervisor chen.
>> aye
>> there are 10 aye's
>> thank you this motion passes
without objection.
Item 26 is approved and sgen 28
are tabled.
>> this concludes our 3 P.M.
Special order and I will hand
the gavel back to PRESIDENT
Mandelman.
>> thank you.
PRESIDENT Protim walton.
>> well.
Thank you supervisor walton.
Okay.
I believe we were in roll call?
Go back to roll call
>> supervisor melgar you would
be next to introduce new
business.
>> I did.
>> supervisor sauter.
>> submit.
>> thank you
>> supervisor sherrill.
>> colleagues today I'm
introducing two items to address
large commercial vacancy in
downtown and on major transit
corridors.
Last week we were dealt a blow
and bloomingdales announced the
closure removing the last
remaining major tenants.
Business came on the heels wall
greens announcing closures
across the city leaving
residence denials to adjust
prescription and drug store need
its is distressing that this
news is not at all enterprising.
.
We have had upon grown used to
flag ships close nothing the
most I conic shopping areas.
Having the learning vacant store
front in trafficked corridors
not only harms public perception
e rhodeses our economic health.
We see this in the slow post
pandemic recovery of sales tax
revenue make it easy to open a
business and thrive in san
francisco.
I'm greatest for the work of
supervisor engardio held a
hearing on tax revenue of
downtown vaccances helping the
recommendifications of the
problem now a hear to further
this work.
The hearing will pokous
identifying ways we on the board
with fill the vacant space
analyzing barriers for tenants
and strategyizing legislative
solutions.
.
This work cannot wait.
When our stoeshs leave the city
we lose needed commercial
activity and tax revenue we lose
morale we must again become the
city of yes withent preneuros
and businesses succeed.
Must reestablish san francisco
as a thriving forward thinking
commercial hub.
I want to thank supervisors
sauter and dorsey for your
cosponsor should.
This hearing william be a step
furthering progress in the post
pandemic recovery and look
forward to working with all of
you to impelement the policy
changes that will catalyze our
economic revitalization.
In addition to the hearing.
I'm introducing an ordinance
that will permit form well
retail on van necessary between
redwood street and broadway.
Van ness exetch fies the type of
opportunity we must have.
Too long we allowed the planning
code full of restrictions now as
we recover from the pandemic we
need tong creative low how to
inject flexibility and welcome
more commercial activity.
This is a response to the many
stories we heard from property
ordinance facing challenges in
filling the space urn the
existing cu requirements.
Currently, there is over 200,000
square feet of vacant retail
pace in this section, lone.
Building owners told my office
that properties remained vacant
for long are than 5 years.
This is in the only to their
financial detriment to the whole
city's will detriment begin how
important van ness is it is
critical we tackle the problems
part of highway 101 and thome
automobile show rooms with large
stow footprints.
However, since the 70s the show
rooms left van ness leaving
large spaces empty and difficult
to occupy.
Despite this, our code restrict
pardon form well retail from
filling the space requiring
store 10 eblts to go through cu
presses.
If a business wants to fill the
vacant store fronts city hall
needs to make it easy to do so
not be ooblt another obstacle.
I want to thank supervisor
sauter district boarders this
section for coexperienceship.
Two initiatives will infuse
manager in our business
landscape and make it easier to
live and thrive in san
francisco.
Thank you
>> thank you
>> supervisor walton
>> thank you.
Colleagues I have a resolution
and two in memories today.
The resolution is urging medical
professionals and existing
furthermoracies to expand
services to under served
neighborhoods.
Over the years the expansion of
chain pharmacies across the city
in the 2,000's lead us to the
closure of many inspect
neighborhood pharmacy.
Closures left gap and acstoesz
essential health care.
And for vulnerable populations
like seniors.
In d 10 many depend on chain
pharmacy for essential healing
service.
With wall greens announcing the
closure of multiple locations,
and including the left 2
remaining pharmacies and
district 10.
Our neighborhoods are now facing
a serious public health crisis.
we are on the brink of a
pharmacy desert.
Access to medications and health
care becomes limited.
We cannot tell our seniors or
residence denials who face
technological bear dwroers order
medications on line or rely on
mail delivery this is an issue.
Equal access to essential health
care service this resolution
callos existing pharmacies and
medical providers to step and up
fill this void.
And insugar no neighborhood is
left when it MISS To equal
health care and medication
access.
I have 2 in memoriums the first
for MRS. Rosa called home on
JANUARY 13, 2025 in san
francisco.
At the age of 66.
Rosa was born on OCTOBER 31,
1958 in guatemala imgreated the
united states in upon 1970.
Rosa's career was dedicate dod
taking care of others.
She started as a nanny.
Love anding caring for the
children she watched as though
they were her own.
As a single mother of 4 she
pursued her ged and learned
english raising her daughters
she became a nursing assistant
upon providing care for the
elderly.
Rosa's resource willness were
unmatched.
She taught herself to drive.
Became involved in her
children's education throughout
pda and served a member of her
tenant association.
She learned add vo indicated for
her community.
Her approximation for advocacy
and helping others earned her
the name, mama rosa.
a title she carried with honest
or she bipartisan a mother
figure to or daughters but to
others in the mission.
The heart of gold and self of
the spirit he welcomed anyone in
need in her life and home.
She shared a love through
cooking and community work.
Rosa's legacy as a community
leader and source of unwaivering
support will live in the hearts
of all who knew her.
Rosa would be missed and
lovingly remembered by family,
friend and the lives she
touched.
Second is for allen beltran made
transition on JANUARY 14 of
2025.
I will mitt this jointly with
supervisors field upper, chan
and chen.
Allen was born in 1979 balboa
hospital in san diego father on
active duty in the navy.
Due to further's naval inial
career he lived in many places.
Early years lived in visitation
valley for a bilt before his
family settle in the vallejo.
Attentived valleto senior high
school and studied at san hose I
state and santa clara university
with a degree in information
systems before joining the tech
industry.
Shortly after he fell had love
and married his wife lori.
Allen enjoys cheering on giants
through 3 world series vict rows
wav war years through 4
championships and bbq's rooting
for the 49ers.
Had a love for the bay area and
the under upon ground hip hop
scene.
His favorite song, 93 until
infinity by souls of mischief.
Had a heart and passion for san
francisco.
He raised his two daughters oshg
live why and victoria.
And enjoyed cups of coffee and
served his community throughout
working families party.
Allen brought so much life,
energy and joy to everyone he
met.
He was the life of the per and a
47 who was willing to lin offer
advice and engage in discussions
about world issues.
It was evidence that he was
allen of the people and a man
who stood by his beliefs and
included everyone.
Inthon did not hesitate to shed
lighta o what was just.
He was not afraid to question,
ask or seek.
Believed this if you fought long
enough you would find the
answer.
He always made time for his
daughters.
Love to play with them, liver to
store and hes reading them
books.
Took pride in being
filipino-american and cherished
filipino-american history.
Survived by wife and tw
daughter, parents, sister and
brother in law.
Niece, nephew, GOD son and a
host of close relatives and
friends who will cherish his
memory.
The rest I submit and I believe
supervisors fielder, chan and
chen have something to say.
>> thank you, supervisor walon.
Supervisor feeler.
>> thank you.
Thank you for reading this.
Allen is san francisco embodied.
He is has been a light, for a
lot in the community and the
policy and politics world, he
just embodies all of the
positivivity and forward looking
and progressive oriented values
of san (I will dopely MISS
Running into him.
And -- I want to share my
thought and prayers with his
family and daughters.
And we will continue on.
Thank you allen.
>> thank you.
Supervisor fielder.
Supervisor chan.
The end.
>> okay.
>> supervisor chen
>> I had the privilege of
meeting allen when he was
volunteers in communities a long
time ago.
He was always ded indicatored
our community and generous and
warm and making connections with
all the people around him.
And had amazing energy to work
on causes he believed in.
And he was also fun to hang out
during social events he left us
too soon.
And my heart breaks for many
friends and family members he
leaves behind.
Especially his wife and young
daughters.
We always remember you allen.
>> thank you.
Supervisor chen.
Supervisor chan.
>> thank you.
MADAM Clerk I first I am
colleagues I'm introducing along
withim grant colleagues and al
ice and partner ship with
chinese affirmative action
condemning trump's order if
birth right citizenship it is in
our constitution under the 14
amendment.
And was reaffirmed over 125
years ago by the landmark U.S.
Procedure decision involving san
francisco born chinese-american
[Inaudible] Denied reentry after
visiting family in china and
given an order of deportation
under the chinese exclusion act.
His legacy and fight for justice
ensure anyone born in the united
states regardless of race, class
or immigration status of their
parents are born in U.S.
Statuses under the U.S.
Constitution.
This constitutional racist and
phobic order from trump
administration will have this
impact on san francisco.
Where one in two children live
nothing our city have at least
oneim grant parent.
We must stand withim grant
community and fight that against
any attempt to under mine our
rights.
This bring me to joining
supervisor walten in rrming
allen bell tron, this is the
fight I can imagine allen will
joining us and would have been
joining us and stand along side
with allis andim grants families
and many and -- with shout loud
and clear about affirming theim
grant rights.
And upon will fight for example
social justicement anybody who
knew allen knew he is tall and
just big and loud.
And grateful for his presence
and the opportunity to have
known him.
And with that to also want said
to concur the sentiment this
supervisor melgar had expressed
for another memory we introduced
today together joint low
forrinea deerman.
And that who's was the mother of
kelly dovermachine or executive
director of department of
disability and aging services.
Having to advance services and
protection to aging population
and her work in this we saw the
legacy offinea deerman she
celebrated her 60th wedding
anniversary to her husband,
together they waysed their son
and two daughters instilled
importance of serving the
community.
Tracie runs the fell's realty
business and nonprofit to
provide first time home buyers
credit card counciling and
assess to afford annual housing.
Jonathan who gives time to local
nonprofit serving our students
and teachers.
Inea was accepted to university
of california berkeley at the
young age of 16 and continued
education achieving a master's
in social work.
Dedicated to serving her
community andom a host of local
boards.
.
Including the land mark
preservation board.
Buttinea loved her family and
community and had a great sense
of humor and always told it like
it is.
She missed by her husband.
Their children and her
grandchildren and many friends
and neighbors.
And the rest I submit.
>> thank you, supervisor chan.
>> MR. PRESIDENT there are no
more names that concludes
introduction.
Supervisor chan
>> that concludes new business.
>> thank you, go to public
comment.
Now time for general public
comment you can peek to the
mayoral appearance the DECEMBER
17 minutes and other items this
are within the board's subject
matter jurisdiction all other
content reported out by
committee.
>> welcome to our first
speaker.
>> you can't think you see
makes you more ugly.
You destroyed your soul doing
it.
I'm going to explain the
[Inaudible] I first want to
congratulate all the new board
of supervisors the PRESIDENT For
talking the oath and oath is
important.
Next saturday I will for the
marine core league and I'm
looking forward to working with
the city of san francisco on all
the needs to make the city great
again.
Everyone should have respected
this document I read the agenda
so it was sent out.
I'm talking about title 4 part
5.
And for a year or long are a
glitch in the system this was
over charging vet residence the
rent.
I urge to you get with the
houses authority I submit third
degree to them they are looking
at it with david chu is aware
there is money visible for san
francisco also for housing.
Well is 120 bilge fund I urge
each of to you electric at this
if you have questions I'm
available off line and thank you
and good luck to the new board.
Next speaker, please.
I'm [Inaudible].
I'm going to give you one advice
to bring prosperity become at
this time city.
Steve job start his computer
went to india.
[Inaudible].
He paid his homage and became
successful.
Then zuk arer
ckerberg had problem.
[Inaudible].
Became successful.
If anyone is interested that
person will go.
I hope.
Steal come back.
Toll me [Inaudible].
Toronto city sued and bailed out
taxi drivers last year
[Inaudible].
New york city bailed out taxi
drivers throw00 million dollars.
If new york can bail out so many
taxi drivers why is san
francisco can't do it?
We are very reasonable.
Our businesses are unstable.
There is no optimism in this
business.
Nothing to achieve.
I expressed men times medallion
250,000100% business now 1%
business at airport.
Thank you for your comments.
Welcome.
>> thank you.
It has been going on years the
taxi issues.
I don't know why you guys are
not really taking it serious.
We are suffering.
We are lost.
Financial low we are lost
physically.
And we are be lost like all
everything -- because of this
business.
And we are stale pay thousand
dollarsands to run it.
There is nothing and I don't
know why it take so language for
city to decide what to do with
the taxi driver.
But it is toll low seriously
from my heart we are suffering
and like we are tired.
16-47 hires of w a day.
Who will do this much?
We are directing for years we
don't have more strength and we
skw you to make an accountable
whoever mt aor somebody and
bring them on table why you are
taking against us and not doing
anything?
We are honestly if you -- tell
the will people they will go
taxi we are not taxi.
They don't look at us.
We don't have a business.
We just please, make accountable
to mt a and bring them together
and fix our problem it has to be
fixed otherwise we will die like
that if we die like this we will
never forgive you guys.
That's what we feel about
temperature thank you.
>> thank you.
Welcome.
>> okay.
I'm leah I live in d6.
I was going to read a chapter
from something from [Inaudible]
About the common experience of
black trans women in prison
unfortunately I don't have that
the board doing a hundred
arrests a night.
Unfortunately the time this
meeting started I got a notice
about another executive order
protecting children from
chemical and surgical mutilation
[Inaudible].
18 and under.
So technically an adult you can
imagine where that will go.
I just seen how y'all I saw how
y'all ignored trans kids in
front of city hall when than I
had I ral and he let the gop and
texan you tube are harass them
grossly.
i saw a movie world war ii you
know typical nazi move theshowed
german living their every day
lives along side the jewish
people who were genocided.
And that struck me.
I feel that is happening noween
in the city.
Where people unaffected are
living their lives while
transpeople and other people,
but I'm focussing on transpeople
here.
Are fearing the wirfs everworst
I will read -- wirfs
orse people hor
legal adults 18 and attempt a
ban at those under 19.
Policies this rely on
[Inaudible].
Thank you.
>> next speaker, please.
I'm mark bruno I live in d throw
since 86 and work with others
for the homeless community since
911.
In 2001 it was not our intention
to work with the homeless we
came as a community for prefer
and find peace a few days in
washington square after 911.
Our program depends on
volunteers one is your new
supervisors sauter, I want to
thank him for volunteer with us.
I believe the proposals made by
the mayor, mayor lurie are add
van ages to the homeless.
They are a way will best
category seen to effective
expedite getting help to the
people on the street.
I have been wearing I coat
because I'm freezing.
I'm old and it is cold.
Every night it has been freezing
for those of you and you then
and there from your response
they want to be on the street or
so-and-so.
i don't believe that is true I
believe the people who claim to
upons to live on the street need
health care.
I have been doing this for 23
years that is since 911.
Reasonable 2 days ago I was
interviewed by rai the italian
station on the fence fential
crisis what is it like in italy
will.
We don't have one but we are
looking at san francisco to find
a solution.
This puts a spotlight on san
francisco.
We are being looked at
throughout the world as the
place where the homeless are.
And we are fentanyl is and gives
us an opportunity the mayor and
all of you to find a solution to
take those risks to find the
compassion and the means to move
quickly to do what I believe can
be done by the new
administration and for this
reason I endorse the mayor's
proposals.
Thank you.
>> next speaker, please.
Hi.
Good afternoon and welcome to
the 5 new supervisors on the
board I'm carolyn and a member
of local 21 and w for the public
defendery office we representim
guarantee and refugees I lived
in san francisco for 20 years
special raised my two kids in
public school.
Thank you to you for your
support as supervisor fielder
resolution affirming our
sanctuary status when I love
benefit this city and makes us
committed to the city are the
things that are under threat.
This is a city and building
where I married my wife major is
like ours legalized before most
other places in the country and
queer and transcommunity feel
home.
This city harvey milk was
elected to office.
This city leadim guarantee
rights the first sanctuary
cities in the country.
Work to protectim grant families
and lead the way for other more
then and there throw 50 other
cities to adopt sanctuary laws
the resolution is so purchase
them is the moment to reaffirm
values and speak out forim grant
community and this morning's
press conference was a beautiful
show of that unity.
We conditional weaken our laws
or add loopholes we seen that
this is how they divide and
conchor.
Thank you supervisor field and
staff and thank you to all
supervisors for affirming the
san francisco valleys this make
this city a beacon of hope and
light.
>> next.
Next speaker, please.
>>
>> I'm amy and I'm a resident
of d8 and a law stunt in san
francisco.
I am here today to talk about
the sanctuary city ordinance and
how important that is to san
francisco particular low for me
I know peers areim fwrn and
their families can be asciied by
the trump administration's
immigration executive orders.
I have always wanted live in san
francisco growing it up is I
pillar of progressive values
inclusivity equality and
dignity.
And I would love to see the city
continue to protectim grnls
because one resident are refumes
and they are pillars of this
city.
And make our community when they
are.
I would hate to see any of my
fellow students not go to school
or misout on important
opportunity because they are
fearful of being deported.
I have worked in legal service
in the communities and I believe
this our sanctuary ordinance
pronotes community safety.
My clients are helped by the
ordinance and they are able to
seek services they need.
The witnesses -- go and scout
rights.
And this is important for them
so they get the help than I
need.
Thank you.
>> thank you.
Next speaker, please.
>> happy new year I'm upon
gregory bell.
Seek defense from racism and
elder, bus at 230 central avenue
that was owned by san francisco
social worker sharon bell I have
been to attentives health
clinics rip boyd landlords or
handy men.
And I have been more than
sympathetic with the sisters it
was not until juneteenth of 2024
when real estate nora radcliffe
and thugs forced their way in my
home.
And then on OCTOBER 22nd of 24.
When one of them smeared his
sh -- in my bedroom.
Just as many women might fear
being raped by a repair man or
city says they must let in if
the land lord sends him.
I ask the san finish board
should lus be made allowing
tenants demand id for background
checks prior to repair dates
refusent row who have a history
of theft or violence.
Refusent row in our homes those
repairmen not state licensed or
bonded.
Require property managers to
employ license female
contractors.
Seek left lanesed female
And then to have present with
the elderly women and families
with children volunteer
chaperons during repair vses by
unknown men I look forward to
speak with my d5 supervisor.
>> thank you.
Next speaker, please.
>> good evening I'm natalie
chen a residents of the mission.
I work in the toin toin for the
left 6 years upon.
We supportim guarantees and are
committed to safety and
protection.
San francisco I pioneer in
upholding values.
The ordinance ensures the values
are protectd and honord and a
commitment to the protection of
all that is marginalized san
francisco.
The report released by american
progress shown crime is low and
economies are stronger compared
to nonsanctuary counselys.
This ordinance ensures our tax
dollars dedicate to stronger and
safe communities.
We are grateful that san
francisco will spearhead
policies in the face unjust
precious as it has in the past
and emcellucciures to dot same
of thank you.
Thank you.
Next speaker, please.
Good afternoon A.M. Carl an
attorney at the asian law caucus
in san francisco china town
where I direct or work on civil
liberties I thank you
supervisors and reaif he wering
our city to the sanctuary
ordinance.
PRESIDENT Trump issued executive
orders how we will take apartim
grant communities enlist law
enforcement and use baseless
legal threat tos scare cities
like san francisco to backing
away from our commitments.
We must not allow fear to over
ride values of inning cluz and
protection for residents.
Sanctuary keeps loved 1 together
and communities safer this is a
time as this body has don double
down keepingim grant community
safe and a time to stay alert
how the trump add station MAY
circumvent the policy.
Left we're's orders are
reshaping the missions of law
enforcement agencies to special
mass deportation.
One federal law enforcement
agency once helped secure unt
for undocumented victims of
human trafficking assigned a
mission of combating the
presence of aliens in the united
states.
New cross agency information
relationship that is considered
by the mayor's office.
Threatens to make information
that san francisco police
department provides to the fbi
you know throughout joint
terrorism task force shared with
ice for deportation purposes.
We need to hold the line against
collaboration with ice.
.
So thank you for your support of
the sanctuary ordinance and stay
alert the administration will
use
>> thank you.
Next speaker, please.
Good afternoon.
I'm with market communicate
action network.
We serve low income working
classim grant families and wars.
San francisco needs to protect
all immigrants they are one of
reason the city runs every day.
Every inn everyone deserves to
feel safe in home, work, school.
Transportation and spaces,
especially in the sanctuary
city.
Upon immigrants are a vital part
of our city.
Our families communities work
place and neighborhoods.
We believe in equality and
opportunity for all.
San francisco should in the use
our local resources to deport
immigrants.
Thank you for your time and your
support.
>> thank you.
Next speaker, please.
>> good afternoon I'm jose I'm
with chinese immigrant right
program manager and serve onim
grant commission as a
commissioner.
Today on behalf I speak in
support of the board's our
city's sanctuary ordinance.
Deep appreciation and gratitude
for the board and the current
supervisor fielder leadership
standing with ourim grant
community.
We are aware of trump
administration antiim grant
agenda.
It executive orders targetingim
grant communes.
In a time like this, it is more
than ever person for us to
remind us about our proud
history as a city of immigrants.
and how we stand up to the
federal government and we are
not the intimidating in
deterring our community.
San francisco ordinance were in
the 90's and the first major
cities in the nation to pass a
sashth iary city now we are
joining 500 city and state
across the country.
It is in the only define whoy
woor as a city of intrusion,
compassion and equality but
ensures our immigrant commuter
access services like what we
shared going to hospital.
Going to school without worried
about turn in the ice or worry
about immigration rate.
Again, we thank you for your
support and hope the board will
continue to support immigrant
community.
Thank you.
>> thank you.
Next speaker, please.
>> good evening I'm catrain
from the filipino communal
center in d11 we are an
organization of the san
franciscoim grant legal and
education network.
I knowim guarantees are a vital
part of our city and fight for
over million undocumented
philippinose in the united
states continuing to live in
fear amidst the new trump
presidency.
Receiving requests for know your
rightsum inauguration training.
Support with plans are receive
notice from community members
they are pressured to self
depofrment without certainty
they will be supported by their
home country governments I want
to thank you for your commit to
san francisco sanctuary
ordinance.
san francisco was the first
sanctuary cities in the country.
Sfi scomplandim grant legal
defense has been a beacon of
hope launching the respectid
response hot line to aid
immigrants targeted by ice.
We want to thank you again for
your commitment to the
immigrants in the city.
We hope for commitment to hold
the da accountable urging an end
to the justice system with
federal agencies.
That results in fast track
deportation and life threatening
conditions for victims of labor
trafficking.
Im grant community deserve
information and services without
fear of racist attacks.
Andure empowered continue to
advocate for better livelihoods.
Next speaker, please.
>> good afternoon I'm jerad I'm
the case managers at the
filipino community center in d
11.
An constitution that service
migrant workers family and youth
we know how vitalim grant
communities are to the heart of
the city.
Our sanctuary ordinance protects
the one in three san francisco
residents who are refugees and
immigrants.
And the ordinance not only
upholds our city's values of
inclusivity, equality and
dignity but ensuresim guarantee
communities are safe and can
participate in our community.
As the only filipino
organization in the san
franciscoim grant legal and
education network, we are able
to provide our community with
resources to help them
understand their rights as
immigrants.
And since the inauguration of
trump there has been fear
throughout our community on his
plans of mass deportations.
I hope that we can puts this
fear that rung throughout our
community at ease.
But we can only do this by
protecting immigrants during
this time and reassuring them
that our city is a safe place
for them and families.
Please uphold san francisco
sanctuary status and protect our
commutes.
Thank you.
Next speaker, please.
I'm angela chan assistant chief
attorney.
I worked at asian law caucus
authored sanctuary laws and
update our ordinance.
I like to express appreciation
to supervisor fielder for
authoring the resolution and the
full board for co-authoring to
affirmim guarantees are vital
and part of our city.
My two dksdz wing on sanctuary
policy.
Every two years an attempt that
attack our ordinance for
political gain.
Issues that have nothing to do
with immigration and each time
san francisco members come up
strong to defend against the
attacks.
Each time we have been success
envelope this board room.
And during the last trump
administration we defends bee
updated the sanctuary ordinance
with the board to keep up be ice
tactics turning our law
enforcement [Inaudible].
Emphasize we are a city that
believes in power not panic.
When we are attacked we stand
up, fight back and get stronger
that's our history.
Also. To point out, upon our
values that right now the da's
office has been colluding with
the U.S. Attorney's office and a
number of federal agencies to
arrest our clients many who have
been trafficked.
Showingly up for court
proceedings feds offering
clients cohearsive deals release
one time plus a day for ice to
pick them up we ask this stop
thunder terrifying trump
administration and san francisco
to stand up.
Thank you.
Welcome.
>> hello supervisors I'm
community engagement at glide
social justice.
Thank you for sppth supervisor
fielder's resolution reaffirming
san francisco commitment to the
sanctuary ordinance.
Glide hospitalsim guarantee who
contribute so much to our
community.
Glide is inclusive and will not
allow for antiim grant rhetoric
to divide us.
All san franciscans upon should
feel safe.
Am we need you as our elected
officials to do more not less to
protect refugee andim guarantees
who are 1 in 3 every san
francisco residents glide is
open to everyone in the city
that is vital to customer a safe
environment to not only access
services but to be part of our
community.
Thank you.
>> thank you.
Next speaker, please.
>> good afternoon I'm andy
stone.
and I'm with the san francisco
aids foundation.
And the hiv advocacy network a
group activist in the bay area
fight to end the epidemic and
improve the lives.
And I wanted share quick thought
in support safrpgs iary city
resolution.
First we stands in fierce
solidarity withim grnltss and in
right to live without foreand be
recognized as a part of your
community.
Mented highlight that cruel
immigration policy like mass
deportation andim grant
attention means death for our
communities lbgtq+ member and
folks who are living with hiv.
Deportation sends people to
place where is it is difficult
to access life saving
medications and targeted for who
they are or health care needs.
Immigrant attention is cruel and
often times denies people access
to life saving medications for
people living with hiv and
caused many deaths.
We must lead as a city in our
values.
And stands up for all of those
targeted.
Thank you supervisor fielder for
introducing this resolution and
the board for standing up and
fighting for our values.
Thank you.
>> thank you.
>> next speaker, please.
>> I'm zanld are breyer a
program specialist and the hiv
network in support for sanctuary
our ordinance uphold our values
of inclusivity.
Equality and dignity refugees
and immigrants comprise 1 of
throw residents and a part of
our city's heart and identity.
i during my day job run support
groups, survival sec workers,
homeless community.
And I am not able to give that
quality care when my clients are
in panic mode wonder if they
will access their life saving
resource.
The law strengthen community
safe and ordinance promotes
community safety.
This long standing law helps
victims and witnesses including
survivors of domestic violence
get the help they need without
fearing of deportation.
The public safety benefits of
sanctuary policies cities and
counties with sanctuary policy
vs less crime we will need
toent the colougz with federal
agencies.
Throughout the past year the san
francisco da collusion with
federal agencies set up a 2
tiered sufficiency justice that
discriminates against and
deprive the immigrants.
Fast track people to deportation
and subjects victims it labor
trafficking to life threatening
continues.
Thank you.
>> thank you.
Next speaker, please.
Welcome.
>> hello.
I'm eva I'm a resident of d 11
work with san francisco rising
and a volunteer with the hiv
advocacy network.
Organizations stand for working
class community.
Communities of color.
Lbgtq+ impact exclude risk for
hiv and protectingim grant
communities is an intersection
of the work that we do.
And what makes san francisco the
diverse city it is.
i want to thank supervisor
fielder and to the board who
named her support.
My favorite thing about san
francisco there are people and
food and culture from all over
the plannest.
I'm not anim grant but I know
what is is like to move across
the world to a new place not
knowing anything the layout of
the geography the available
social assistance and healing
service programs let alone
understanding the political left
lane scapeful and we than
everyone in the city is safer
when they don't have to fear
legal consequences and
deportation when accessing make
health care.
I volunteer at sf rising and
grown my career and family in
the city.
I'm here to echo the comments
made by pierce this afternoon
regarding our reaffirming san
francisco as a sanctuary city.
Decades our city hope, dignity
and he safety for immigrants.
Immigrants are not outsiders
neighbors, coworkers and friends
they build economy and culture
and make san francisco the
vibrant diversity we are proud
to call home.
Turning our back would betray
the soul of our city.
Thank you for your time.
>> thank you.
Welcome.
Good afternoon I'm speaking on
behalf of the sanctuary city
ordinance.
Thank you entires feel and all
supervisors for your support.
The moment in time for you all
know it is important make sure
there are no loophole in
ordinance it is important.
benefits public safety and
community our boundless I
appreciate that as well.
Pierce stated intersection with
lbgtq+ folks and folks with hiv
is important this issue I thank
you for that action on this.
We have to end the colougz with
the da and federal agents to
make sure or city is safe and
community members are protected
in the way that equal to sf
values thank you.
Thank you.
Welcome employs
>> good afternoon.
Congratulations.
PRESIDENT Mandelman nice to sigh
I'm michael.
I will speak in two capacity in
support of item 37 the sanctuary
city resolution.
Based on supervisor fielder.
At the covice PRESIDENT Of
political affairs latin
congresses democratic club we
speak in support of this and
like to see hear issues that are
tackled.
We 99 study after study sashgs
eversanct iary cities show the
laws keep people and families
safer we want to see this
continue and more victims and
effort made on your behalf.
Whether it is to keep our
families housed.
Additional funning in additional
funding from ocd would be
helpful for more affordable
housing and addressing the
da'sing
da's
da'sing.
I will also say that I'm
concerned when I see
partnerships with organizations
that are openly hostile toward
people with hiv and aids well
are many immigrants who are
survivors with aids. Language
includes integrity competence
community.
Those mead to be complied with
and should look at that when
enacting the oranges.
Thank you.
Have a great day.
Vehicle.
>>s I'm sarah lee an organizer
with theim grant resource center
and the coalition that advocated
and defended san francisco
sanctuary orns I'm here to
support this residence luge.
Grateful to seat board's support
and the press conference this
morning.
I want to flag that we must be
vigilent the ways agencies seek
to violate this on sanctuary.
Others here who have shared
about the the collusion with
federal agencies detailed where
well is a fast track of
deportation happening in the
city and resulted in krours
arrests outside 850 bryant in
the past year.
The arrests we have seen the
rumors and fierce that the
immigrant community face instead
past weeks and the arrests will
exacerbate that pay attention to
the da collusion with the
federal agencies they will
exacerbate fear instead of more
safety.
Thank you.
Next speaker, please.
I'm erin meek in d 8.
I'm a mother, and intermission
the first thing here in special
policy because I will have an
image burned senor olds crying
for fear of taken from parents.
during the first trump
administration.
The way families are suffering
is inexcusable we have to
support them.
Supervisor fielder I appreciate
you bringing this policy and
appeals to know they are safe
and it a family living with us
of a mixed status family the
kids were worried their parents
will be torn from them.
I'm a health researcher I take
opportunity to share data we
know that in our latin x section
minor communities hiv on the
rise in latin america and here.
If we don't make the policies
clear and show we are enforcing
sanctuary policies zeal risks of
hiv and fewer in treatment for
fear of deperation.
Need to get people the health
care they mead to keep our city
health competence supported hiv
prevention.
Thank you again.
I can't affirm this stronger but
our policies need to show out in
the community.
I encourage you to do this,
thank you.
>> thank you.
Welcome.
>> good afternoonful I'm
beverly with the san francisco
domestic violence.
I want to thank supervisor field
and all of you for your support
of sustaining the sanctuary city
work in san frat domestic
violence consortium work nothing
favor of sanctuary city for 20
years.
Most survivors of do meteck
violence domestic violence
partners deported they want to
change behavior and lead noni
have 11 lives we are hear to
passport this.
we are in favor of keeping san
francisco sanctuary city
ordinance and also we are
worried about the chilling
affect of reaching out for help
if survivors cannot trust san
francisco to protect their
families.
So.
We are here to thank you for
leadership this will be a long
road.
We are also seeing things that
will hurt violence, trafficking,
I look forward to working with
you close low in the future.
Thank you.
Welcome
>> hear in support of item 37.
I'm the state wide organizing
manager for immigrant policy
center we work withim grant
organizations and advocate in
san francisco I'm he were part
of the solution.
I stand with the immigrant
community in san francisco and
contributions to arts and
industries and infrastructure.
It is clear that san francisco
is a beacon of immigrant
entrepreneurship.
My respect to add vo indicateds
and policy makers pushed for the
framework organizing advocacy
and resources to integrate
community and keep families
together the immigrant policy
center affirms sanctuary locals
but more must be done end
collusion with federal agencies
and defends the advancements of
civil society.
Thank you.
Next speaker, please I'm a
students and voltory at san
francisco rising.
It I'm here to confront the harm
on the people in the city I am
native american.
in my culture we don't believe
this land can be bought we are
all nature and meant to heart,
mind and soul we provide.
Before speak here I was afraid I
did not have the knowledge or
education to display.
It does not take toejz
understands the safetied we must
provide for children and people.
I am afraid in a country that my
people have found and yet we are
harming so many people who don't
deserve this.
So I ask please protect us keep
our kids and families safe.
We are not going with each
other.
And we are growing against which
is something this native
american don't value at all.
Which is the lack of love and n
our communities.
So I kindly ask, please, be a
little open minded and a little
mindful of people of hearts.
Of children.
Thank you
>> thank you.
Welcome, next speaker, please.
Good afternoon san francisco
supervisors congratulations on
the new supervisors hello
returning supervisors.
I think no secret I'm one of the
few trump supporters in san fran
I like like to clarify my family
left england in 17 nic and came
to the country.
I think there is a disconnect
between american citizens and
migrants citizens are a race of
people of all races and
religions.
I think you know it is person to
understand millions of people
entered our country illegally
the last few years those
resources that went to them
could have gone to american
citizens.
Walking in the streets of san
francisco and seeing illegalim
grants from honduras selling
fentanyl.
Illegalim grants from honduras
are responsible for deaths of
4,000 american citizen of all
races and religions.
Yea I like to say
congratulations PRESIDENT Trump
on a successful victory.
Today in the tenderloin I seen
ice out there arresting the
fentanyl deal and look forward
to them getting deported I have
love and respect for fellow
sfranz miguarantees are west b
oast earth if you are coming in
to ecploy our city to sell
fentanyl you will be deported.
This will be our last speaker.
Many san franciscans regardless
of income find it difficult to
afford rehab in addiction.
The purpose of de
[Inaudible]
Busting on a tight budget to the
camp mather.
And 4 weeks 1200 residents
acomtated over 9 months through
the.
Sheriff's recommendation through
self referral and through
clinical approval.
Today's support organizations
about sen00 or ineffective.
Camp mather and related
facilities have enjoyed equity
in investment but restrictions
and I percent of residents
ac-
ess and enjoy public,
commendation in striking
contrast to the restrictions
many hotel now in receivership
took in a homeless during the
pandemic.
Thank you.
No other speakers MR. PRESIDENT.
>> all right.
Public comment is you in closed.
Go to our adoption without
reference agenda 35-41.
35-front introduced for adoption
without reference a unanimous
vote is required on first
reading today a member MAY
require a resolution on first
read to go to commit eye.
>> all right.
Supervisor walton.
>> thank you.
PRESIDENT Mandelman can we sever
item 38.
>> dorsey
>> thank you.
PRESIDENT Mandelman can I sever
item thing.
I dope see anyone else.
O severing 36 and 38 and on the
remaining items MADAM Clerk call
the roll.
>> item 35, then, 39, 40 and
41.
Entires dorsey.
>> aye.
>> supervisor engardio.
>> aye
>> supervisor fielder.
>> aye.
>> supervisor mahmood.
>> supervisor mandelman.
>> aye.
>> supervisor melgar.
Why aye.
>> supervisor sauter.
>> ayech
>> supervisor sherrill.
>> aye
>> supervisor walton.
>> aye.
>> supervisor chan.
>> supervisor chen.
>> aye.
There are 11 aye's.
>> thank you.
Without objection the
resolutions are adopted.
And -- thena takes us become to
item 36.
>> a resolution on authorize
the closure of the public
sidewalk on both sides of howard
between third and fourth.
From OCTOBER 11-17 of 2025
issuing a permit for the event.
Why supervisor dorsey
>> thank you, PRESIDENT Machine
man.
Colleague this is which is
similar to one the board
unanimously passed left we're
among the necessary city actions
to support the operations of the
dream force convention.
Some of you MAY know following a
successful 2024 convention
signed aly year agreement to
hold it at mos sceney center
lending our downtown businesses
and economic come back.
Conventions play a role in the
downtown economy bringing foot
traffic and boosting business
and supporting the tax base and
few are larger or more to the
city than dream force draws
150,000 from more 120 countries.
I'm thrilled see sales force
recommitment to the home town of
the city and sales force signed
a commitment I'm informd that
this resolution is one we vote
on every year.
So I want to thank my returning
clothes for support and thanks
to new colleagues who support I
hope to earn on this resolution.
>> thank you.
Supervisor dorsey.
I think we same house same call
without objection the resolution
passes.
And then MADAM Clerk we're going
to item threat
>> resolution to urge wall green
reconsider store closures and
prioritize alternative solutions
to maintain their presence.
.
In vulnerable neighborhoods that
face challenge in accessing
health care and essential
service.
Supervisor walton
>> thank you.
Colleagues.
It is with concern and
disappointment we acknowledge
the closure of the last two wall
greens location in d 10.
Located at 5300, third and 11
kwaen potrero
>> they contribute to 12 with
you green shut downs across san
francisco.
Marking a loss for our
communities.
For years the stores viling
resources and especially after
they force inspect neighborhood
pharmacies to shutter.
The stores provided medication.
House hold goods and person care
to residence denials.
Seniors low income families and
those with limited mobility.
Our office met with the wall
greens represent and will inform
the closures are final with no
room for negotiation or
reconsideration even if lease
reduction were offered the
answer was still, no.
The decision under scores a
trend of pharmacy closure
turning neighborhoods to deserts
and leaving under served
communities with few are options
for critical service healing
service needs.
As mentioned earlier we cannot
tell residents especially
seniors and those facing
technological barriers to
ordonline or rely on mailorder
service this is an issue.
equal access to health care and
essential service.
As a city we must commit to
addressing the needs of all
residents those in historically
underserved communities.
Recognize frustration and
heardship the closures bring and
urge wall greens leadership and
including the ceo and the share
holders to reconsider the
decision and extend the closure
time line to allow the community
and the city time to find
alternatives.
I like to thank all cosponsors
on this resolution and look
forward to working with all of
you and the mayor's office to
find a solution to address the
pharmacy deserts in san
francisco.
Thank you.
>> I think we can take this
item same house same call
without objection it passes.
And -- do we agenda items?
No, MR. PRESIDENT.
>> could you read the in
memorium.
Adjourn in the memories of
following.
On behalf of engardio the late
MRS. Sue d knoll.
On behalf of supervisor and
PRESIDENT Mandelman the late MR.
Damien goldstein on behalf
supervisor walton per rosa limb
and on behalf of supervisor
walon and fieldser, chan and
chen, the late allen beltran.
On a motion on the board of
supervisors for the late ina
deerman.
Thank you.
Is there do we have further
business.
>> that concludes our business
for today.
>> all right.